<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hell open'd, or, The infernal sin of murther punished being a true relation of the poysoning of a whole family in Plymouth, whereof two died in a short time : for which horrid fact, the malefactors were condemned before the Lord Chief Justice North at Exector, the last Lent assizes, the one to be burnt, the other to be hanged : with an account of the several discourses and religious means used by divers godly ministers to bring them to repentance ... / by J.Q., Minister of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Quick, John, 1636-1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 193 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56903</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Q207</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11200</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13012207</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13012207</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96502</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56903)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96502)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 397:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hell open'd, or, The infernal sin of murther punished being a true relation of the poysoning of a whole family in Plymouth, whereof two died in a short time : for which horrid fact, the malefactors were condemned before the Lord Chief Justice North at Exector, the last Lent assizes, the one to be burnt, the other to be hanged : with an account of the several discourses and religious means used by divers godly ministers to bring them to repentance ... / by J.Q., Minister of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Quick, John, 1636-1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 3-96 p., [1] leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Eglesfield ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The epistle" signed: John Quicke.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [16].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Poisoning --  England --  Plymouth</term>
               <term>Poisoners --  England --  Plymouth</term>
               <term>Murder --  England --  Plymouth (Devon)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:96502:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96502:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>scenes of the poisoning; sickness; execution</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>HELL OPEN'D, OR, <hi>The Infernal Sin of Murther Puniſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEING A True Relation of the Poyſoning of a whole Family in <hi>Plymouth,</hi> whereof Two died in a ſhort time.</p>
            <p>For which horrid Fact, the Malefactors were Condemned before the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>North</hi> at <hi>Exceter,</hi> the laſt <hi>Lent</hi> Aſſizes. The one to be Burnt, the other to be Hanged.</p>
            <p>WITH An Account of the ſeveral Diſcourſes, and Religious means uſed by divers godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to bring them to Repentance.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for a warning to both Young and Old, to flie Iniquity, and exerciſe themſelves in the practice of Godlineſs.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. Q.</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Eglesfield,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Marygold</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard, 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="verses">
            <pb facs="tcp:96502:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <q>
               <p>The fear of the Lord is a fountain of life, to depart from the ſnares of death.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 14.27.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>A Man that doth violence to the Blood of any Perſon, ſhall flee to the Pit, let no Man ſtay him.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 28.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>The Lord is known by the judgment which he execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: the wicked is ſnared in the work of his own hands.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 9.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, without (the Gates of Heaven) are the Dogs, and the POYSONERS.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 22.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>And they became a Sign.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Numb. 26.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>And Iſrael ſhall hear, and fear, and do no more ſuch wickedneſs.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut. 13.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:96502:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful <hi>John Dell</hi> Major, and to the Worſhipful <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Weeks, William Jennings,</hi> and <hi>John Martyn,</hi> Juſtices of the Peace, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their Brethren the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates of the Town of <hi>Plymouth.</hi> And to my very Honored Friend, <hi>John Harris</hi> of <hi>Manniton</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have real ſomewhere of an <hi>Hermite,</hi> who being guided by an Angel unto two Cities, ſaw the Gates of the firſt cloſe ſhut, and a Devil having the Keys there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of at his Girdle in a deep ſleep, and ſnort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, From thence he is led unto the other, (which was fair and ſpacious,) and finds the Gates wide open, innumerable Devils crouding and thronging in, multitudes climbing over the walls, and whole ſwarms of them in the Churches, Streets, Houſes, Shops, walks, and all other Avenues
<pb facs="tcp:96502:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>and places of concourſe, exceedingly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, buſying and beſtirring themſelves to the utmoſt for the ruine of it, and her Inhabitants. At which wondring be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond meaſure, the Angel told him, yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der City is the worſt of the Two, ingulpht in all wickedneſs and irreligion, ſo that <hi>Beelzebub</hi> hath no fear of looſing it, and therefore there is but one Devil to guard it, and his work ſo little, that he ſleeps. But as for this wherein now we are, here are many Souls fearing and ſerving God, Religion is profeſſed, and Religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip countenanced and incouraged, and the Holy Angels of God are watching over theſe precious Saints and their Habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to preſerve them. This hath cauſed Hell to break looſe, and to endeavor by all means, and arts imaginable their ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, and its deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Sirs, I think this be no unfitting Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem of our <hi>Plymouth,</hi> wherein I truſt there are multitudes of Gods dear Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, as well as Sinners: But I fear me, multitude of Devils alſo, that walk in
<pb facs="tcp:96502:3"/>Temples and Congregations, in Streets and Houſes, in Chambers and Cloſets, in Ships and Shops, upon Keys and Exchange. The over abounding of Sin among us, and of late of that hainous and crying ſin of Blood and Murther, (for which Two of the prime Actors (and God knows whether there be any other) have ſuffered condign puniſhment,) is too ſad and clear an inſtance hereof. When <hi>Hannibal</hi> was at the Gates of <hi>Rome,</hi> it was more than time for the Conſuls and Senate to look about them. Woe! Woe! Unto the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Earth, ſaith an Angel from Heaven, Becauſe the Devil is come down among you, having great wrath, for his time is ſhort. He doth not appear in a viſible ſhape at noon day, but walks (as his younger Son the <hi>Jeſuite</hi>) in all ſorts of Maſques and diſguiſes, in every habit and faſhion, and among Perſons of every Trade, Calling, Quality, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p>Now, Sirs, God having conſtituted you the <hi>Angel-Guardians</hi> of our <hi>Plymouth,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:96502:4"/>and made you Gods unto it, there is all reaſon you ſhould be awake, and do your utmoſt to prevent the Stratagems and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of Hell againſt it. I know no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way or means that you have, than by an exemplary Holineſs in your lives, than by walking with God in your reſpective Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies and Callings, than by a couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, zealous, activity for God and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and a vigorous ſuppreſſion, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial puniſhing of all Vice and Impiety. Would you but continue your great reſpects and incouragements to your Reverend and Learned Miniſters, and joyn both Swords together, Temporal and Spiritual, I am confident the deſigns of Hell againſt you would be broken, fruſtrated, and render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ineffectual.</p>
            <p>Honored Sirs, My hearts deſire and Prayer for you is, that you may do wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily in your <hi>Ephrata,</hi> and Famouſly in your <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> that you may glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God in your Station, and that God may reflect rays and beams of Glory upon you, <hi>For ſuch as Honor him, God
<pb facs="tcp:96502:4"/>will Honor them, but they that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe him ſhall be lightly eſteemed, 1 Sam. 2.30.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sirs, if you will ſuppreſs all prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and by your Authority put out the Fire of uncleanneſs, if you will ſtop the Mouth, and Gag the Tongue of the Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that the Roaring of Oaths and Curſes be not heard in our Streets, if you will promote true practical Piety, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere as you have begun in the conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſcharge of your Magiſtratical Duty, the God of bleſſings will bleſs your perſons and Families, and <hi>Plymouth</hi> ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be a <hi>Sodom</hi> but <hi>Zion,</hi> ſhall ever be a, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for Goſpel-priviledges, a Pillar and Ground of Truth, rich and flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as <hi>Tyre</hi> for Trade and Traffick, and as formerly, ſo in after-times a <hi>Zoar</hi> for Divine ſafety and wonderful preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>That endeared affection I have for the Town of my Nativity, where I firſt drew my breath, and where I had my School-Education, moveth me to ſpeak
<pb facs="tcp:96502:5"/>and write ſo freely. And your true good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs cannot but make a candid interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof.</p>
            <p>May <hi>Plymouth,</hi> her Magistrates and Government ever live before God! May this Famous Town be called <hi>Hephzibah</hi> and <hi>Beulah,</hi> the <hi>Delight of God, and Married</hi> unto God! Let her be called the Righteous, the Holy City! And may this be her name unto Poſterity, <hi>Jehovah Shamma, The Lord is there.</hi> So prayeth, Right Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ored Sirs.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my Study in <hi>Plymouth,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>April 7. 1676.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt humble and unfeigned Sevant in our Lord Jeſus,</hi> John Quicke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:96502:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE</head>
            <p>THe Devil is ſtiled by our bleſſed Saviour. <hi>A Murderer from the beginning;</hi> Having deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf by his willful A poſtacy from God, and being juſtly baniſhed the Glories of the celeſtial Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe for his Voluntary Rebellion, he turned about him, ſeeking how and in what manner he might be revenged on his Judg. And after all his rueful thoughts and conſultations could find no expedient more likely to ſucceed and take than the <hi>working miſchief on man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our firſt Parents a Compendium of both Worlds, Sublunary and Aetherial, the Crown of Gods Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>but a little lower than the Angels,</hi> are become the objects of his rage and fury. Satan had loſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and he envies them Earth. Their habitation in an Earthly Heaven diſpleaſeth him, becauſe it pleaſeth God. They juſt now came out of their <hi>Creators hands</hi> endowed with a double Portion, Holyneſs and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: But he reſolves they ſhall not long enjoy either. Hence in the very firſt <hi>dawn</hi> of their Creation, he contrived and accompliſhed their deſtruction. He ſubtilly inſinuates the poyſon of ſin by his conferences with, and ſuggeſtions unto <hi>Eve,</hi> and ſhe having once taſted of the doſe, and allured with the deceitful pleaſantneſs thereof to her ſenſual appetite, commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicates it to her Husband, and they both derive it down unto all their natural poſterity.</p>
            <p>Ah! How many Murders were in this One? Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind made and ruined altogether. Certainly they who plotted the blowing up of King and Kingdom in One hour, they who effected the <hi>Sicilian Veſpers,
<pb facs="tcp:96502:6"/>Pariſian Mattins, and Iriſh Maſſacres</hi> had been all trained up and Educated in the Schools of this, this old, and Grand <hi>Abaddon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adam</hi> being in Honor, continued not a day in it. His glorious ſtate did ſhine, and ſet with the ſame Sun. In the Morning it flouriſhed and grew up, in the Evening it was cut down and withered like the Graſs. He played away (as a beſorted Gameſter) his whole, and all preſent and to come, what he had in poſſeſſion, what he might have in Reverſion, at one caſt. Nothing was left him but his ſin and curſe, and this he propagates unto all his Children. (A moſt ſad Portion) to be inherited by us.</p>
            <p>Sin being now conceived doth prodigiouſly ſpawa and ſwarm. The Old Serpent is not idle. His boil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing malice gives him no reſt. His firſt born like the Plague ſpreads its venom univerſally, and new Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are hatched and produced by it every day. New ſins in new ſhapes, in odious and hideous colours ſhew forth their heads. Grace is modeſt. Sin im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent and ſhameleſs: It ſeeketh no diſguiſe, nor putteth on a Vizard, but for its own ſecurity, and in order to further miſchief, to perpetrate ſome greater Villany.</p>
            <p>The Devil having ſet variance between God and Man, will give another caſt of his Office: He throws a Bone of contention between Man and Man. The neareſt Relations, the deareſt Friends, they that had the ſame fleſh in their Bodies, the ſame blood in their veins, that if not Twins yet ſcarce divided in their age, that were Nurſt, Fed, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducated together, both alike tendered by their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent and Religious Parents, ſhall yet through his ſubtilty and cruelty be ſundered and divided one from the other: And if he cannot drag them both with himſelf into Hell, yet will he precipitate
<pb facs="tcp:96502:6"/>the one by a bloody and Barbarous death into his untimely Grave, and the other (by a ſin like his own) into the bottomleſs Pit of deſtruction ere he is aware of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cain</hi> by the inſtigation of the wicked one, upon no provocation, no offence given, (unleſs Gods gracious acceptance of <hi>Abel</hi> for his Faith and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs be a crime,) Murthers his own, his only and deareſt Brother. Bloody Villain! Thou choppeſt off thy right hand with thy left, thou daſheſt out thine own Brains in daſhing out his. Thou deſtroyeſt his, body, but damneſt thine own Soul. Ah, what grief it this to Pious <hi>Adam!</hi> Oh, what joy and Muſick unto Hell! Revenge is ſweet. But its a poor revenge, Satan! Which ends hi thine own, in thine endleſs deſtruction.</p>
            <p>However the Devil hath ſhown the way of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering, and bad Arts are ſoon learnt. Any one may be an eaſie and early proficient in Ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the whole and old World ſoon got the skill of it. God ſaw that the wickedneſs of man was great in the earth, and that every imagination of the thoughts of his heart was only evil continually. The Earth alſo was corrupt before God, and filled with Violence: All fleſh had perverted its way, and blood touched blood.</p>
            <p>There was no fair and gentle means left uneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayed by God to reclaim ſinners, to dam up, if poſſible, the torrents of their ungodlineſs, to ſtench thoſe foul iſſues, and frequent effuſions of Innocent blood. <hi>Adam,</hi> and the Holy Patriarks decry it down in their Lives and Sermons. <hi>Enoch</hi> (the <hi>Phoenix</hi> of his Age for the life and power of Godlineſs ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt illuſtriouſly in his Converſation) Thunders out Propheſies of dreadful Judgments againſt the irreligious <hi>Cainites. Behold,</hi> ſaith that Glorious
<pb facs="tcp:96502:7"/>Saint, <hi>The Lord cometh with Holy Myriads of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels to Execute vengeance upon all the ungodly, and to convince you of your ungodlineſs in flames of Fire, who will not be convinced by our Miniſtry. Upon the wicked he ſhall Rain Snares, Fire, and Brimſtone, and an horrible Tempeſt, This ſhall be the Portion of their Cup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Prophet is counted a Fool, and the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual man Mad, and his Menaces of approaching wrath idle Dreams, melancholly thoughts, bugbears to fright Children, and bublings up of his envy and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt them. Thus he and his Prophecies are deſpiſed, and ſcornfully rejected.</p>
            <p>At laſt fair warning and loud calls and Summons unto Repentance having been long afforded them, and not accepted, nor in the leaſt improved, the patience of God is tired, mercy finally departs from them, and Divine Juſtice ſweeps away the Habitations and perſons of thoſe Scarlet Sinners with a deluge of Waters.</p>
            <p>One would have thought that ſuch a fearful Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould have cautioned afterages from ever tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their ſteps. But alas! Poſterity is grown ſtupid, and Judgment-proof. As for Gods Judgments the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed makes a puff at them, they are afar off, above, and out of his ſight, he forgets and makes no reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor account of them. God hath Hanged up ſome in Chains before their eyes, Executed a whole World of Malefactors, and made them an everlaſting <hi>Sign and Example</hi> to them, yet they willfully ſhut their eyes that they may not ſee, and lock up the Doors of their hearts, that they may not conſider for what cauſes this great wrath is come upon them. So that we need not wonder at Gods plaguing ſuch willful blind Souls. It is but a righteous Retribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that his Juſtice oweth them. In as much as they
<pb facs="tcp:96502:7"/>regarded not the works of the Lord, nor took notice of the operation of his hand, he could not build them up, he muſt totally and utterly deſtroy them. Sinners ate the Voluntary Carvers of their own mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes. They chooſe and Create unto themſelves their own bane and deſtruction, Temporal and Eternal. The reading of this enſuing Narrative will be a clear proof and evidence hereof.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:96502:8"/>
            <head>Books Printed for, and are to be Sold by <hi>Francis Eglesfield,</hi> at the <hi>Marygold</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>DIvi Britannici,</hi> being a Remark upon the Lives of all the Kings of this Iſle, from the year of the World 855. Unto the year of Grace, 1660. By Sir <hi>Winſton Churchill</hi> Knight, in Folio.</p>
            <p>The Works of that Famous Mathematician Maſter <hi>Edmond Gunter,</hi> ſomtimes Profeſſor of <hi>Greſham</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>London.</hi> Reprinted, Corrected, and much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged in this Fifth Edition, in Quarto.</p>
            <p>The whole Art of Dyalling. By <hi>Samuel Foſter,</hi> much enlarged in the Second Impreſſion, in Quarto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aeſops Fables</hi> in Proſe and Verſe, Grammatically Tranſlated with apt Morals, according to the Order of the Latine Copy, together with his Life, in Twelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London Drolery,</hi> or Wits Academy, in Octavo.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Grandure,</hi> and Glory of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dugards Engliſh Rudiments</hi> of the Latine Tongue Explained, in Octavo—</p>
            <p>—His <hi>Rhetoricae Elementae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clarks Formulae Oratoriae,</hi> in Twelves.</p>
            <p>—His <hi>Dux Grammaticus, Dux Oratorius,</hi> in Twelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chiſhuls</hi> Works in Three Parts, in Twelves.</p>
            <p>A Map of <hi>England,</hi> with all the Kings ſince the Conqueſt about it, with a brief Deſcription of them.</p>
            <p>Divine Emblems, and Hieroglyphicks, by <hi>Franch Quaries,</hi> in Octavo.</p>
            <p>Spare Minutes, or Divine Meditations, by <hi>Arthur Warwick,</hi> in Four and Twenties.</p>
            <p>The perfect way to die in peace, by <hi>Ed. Burghall,</hi> in Octavo.</p>
            <p>Steps to the Altar, or a Treatiſe on the Sacrament, by Doctor <hi>Prior,</hi> in Twelves.</p>
            <p>The Covenant of Grace, by <hi>John Cotton,</hi> the Third Edition much enlarged, in Octavo.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="narrative">
            <pb facs="tcp:96502:8"/>
            <head>THE NARRATIVE.</head>
            <p>ON Munday the <hi>23</hi> day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, <hi>1675. Elizabeth,</hi> the Wife of Mr. <hi>William Weeks</hi> of <hi>Plymouth Dyer,</hi> after many and frequent Vomitings and violent Purgations, departed this life towards the Evening. Her Husband and Daughter were ſeized with the ſame extraordinary motions, accompanied with griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pains and Swellings in their Stomacks, with cold Sweats and Faintings, as alſo with a great and unquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Drought.</p>
            <p>A Phyſitian being called, and conſulted with upon the caſe, giveth in his Judgment that they were Poyſoned. That which induced him the more readily to determine of the nature and manner of their Sickneſs, and her death, was a quantity of <hi>Crude Arſenick,</hi> preſented him by a Neighbor of theſe Afflicted and Murthered Perſons, which ſhe had found in a Pot of Oatmeal in the Kitchin.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time the Child of Miſtris <hi>Pengelley</hi> (Daughter unto the ſaid Mr. <hi>Weeks</hi>) was alſo affected with the ſame Symptoms, and <hi>Philip Cary</hi> her Nurſe, together with her Husband, were found Counterfeiting Sickneſs and Vomitings. Wine and Oyl had been given them, which procured a more eaſie relaxation and diſcharge of their Stomacks, and through the Bleſſing of God, upon the uſe of that and other means contributed, to the recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Child and his Grand-Father. Only his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Miſtris <hi>Pengelley,</hi> having labored Eight or Ten days under exquiſite torments without any remiſſion, (Phyſick, and Phyſitians being diſabled by Gods Holy wiſe Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, from affording her any relief or ſuccor,) ſhe alſo yielded up the Ghoſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:96502:9"/>
            <p>The noiſe of this horrid Accident was ſoon ſpread abroad, and immediately the Nurſe and her Husband, and a Prentice Girle in the Houſe were ſuſpected, and apprehended for it.</p>
            <p>The firſt which was brought before the Major of the Town, was <hi>Anne Evans</hi> Apprentice to the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Weeks,</hi> a Poor Child, whoſe Mother being dead, had been bound out in the Majoralty of Mr. <hi>Peter Schaggel,</hi> Anno <hi>1672.</hi> by the Church-Wardens and Over-Seers of <hi>Charles</hi> Pariſh, being then about Twelve or Thirteen years old.</p>
            <p>And now making her appearance, ſhe was examined by him, and another Juſtice of his Majeſties Peace; which for the ſatisfaction of my Readers curioſity, and for a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcovery of this Crying and Helliſh ſin, I ſhall crave his pardon, if he be troubled with an Authentick Relation thereof, and of the other perſons depoſitions concerning it, as they were tranſcribed from the day Book of the Town.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="information">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96502:9"/>
            <head>The Examination and Information of <hi>Anne Evans</hi> of <hi>Plymouth</hi> Spinſter, taken before the Right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>William Weeks</hi> Major of <hi>Plymouth,</hi> and <hi>William Jennings</hi> Merchant, two of his Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace, within the ſaid <hi>Burrough, 25.</hi> Auguſt. <hi>l675.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE ſaid Examinant ſaith, that ſhe being ſent on <hi>Thurſday</hi> laſt by her Maſter, <hi>William Weeks</hi> Dyer, to buy ſome<note n="*" place="margin">Oatmeal.</note> Girts in the Market, ſhe this Examinant accordingly did buy a Pottle of <hi>Joan</hi> the Wife of <hi>George Searle,</hi> and brought them home to her Maſters Houſe, and put ſome of the ſame<note n="*" place="margin">Oatmeal.</note> Girts into the Pot to make Pottage the Sunday following, and this Informant further ſaith, that at Noon ſhe laded up a Diſh of Pottage to her Maſter, and a Diſh to her Miſtris, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Wife to the ſaid <hi>William Weeks,</hi> and alſo a Diſh of Pottage for her ſelf, and <hi>John Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelley</hi> Son of <hi>Mary Pengelley;</hi> and this Examinant fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, that after her Miſtris had eaten the Pottage, ſhe did complain in her Stomack, Head and Belly, and ſaid that ſhe was very Sick, and then ſhe preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Vomited very much, and about an hour after ſhe went to Bed, and kept continually Vomiting and Purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing till Munday laſt, and in the Evening ſhe died, and her Maſter then alſo Vomited, and Purged, and lieth now a Bed very Sick, and alſo ſaith, that ſhe waſhing ſome of the Girts afterwards, ſhe found ſome Yellow thing in the Girts, and as this Informant was told by ſome people, that it was Poyſon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The Sign of <hi>Anne Evans, A. E.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="information">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96502:10"/>
            <head>The Information of <hi>Gray Holland</hi> Doctor in Phyſick, taken as aforeſaid on Oath.</head>
            <p>THe ſaid Informant ſaith, that on Munday laſt, being the three and twentieth day of this inſtant <hi>Auguſt,</hi> about Nine of the Clock in the Evening, he being ſent for to come to the Houſe of <hi>William Weeks</hi> of this Town Dyer; This Informant was by the people of the Houſe informed concerning the death of the ſaid Maſter <hi>Weeks</hi> his Wife, who told him that ſhe was taken with Vomiting, Scouring and Purging, and ſaith, that the ſaid <hi>William Weeks</hi> Dyer, being a Bed Sick, he asked him how he did, who told him, that he had a great pain in his Stomack, and that he was ſwollen in his Stomack, and whatſoever he did take, he did Vomit it up again; And this Informant further ſaith, that he going into a Chamber to ſee Miſtris <hi>Mary Pengelley;</hi> who told this informant, that ſhe had a very great pain in her Stomack, and was ſwollen, and that ſhe was taken with violent Purging and Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting, and cold Sweats, and Faintings, with great drought; And this Informant being ſo informed, he judged that there was Poyſon in the Caſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon deſired to make an inquiry concerning it; And this Informant farther ſaith, that yeſterday in the Morning, one Miſtris <hi>Hurd</hi> bringing to him ſomething which ſhe had taken out of ſome of the Girts, which was put in the Portage; This Informant judged it to be Poyſon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Gray Holland</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="information">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96502:10"/>
            <head>The Information of <hi>Mary</hi> the Wife of <hi>James Hurd</hi> of <hi>Plymouth</hi> Merchant, taken as aforeſaid on Oath.</head>
            <p>THe ſaid Informant ſaith, that ſhe was ſent for to come to the Houſe of <hi>William Weeks</hi> Dyer, on Sunday laſt paſt, and when this Informant came to the ſaid Houſe, ſhe met with Miſtris <hi>Pengelley,</hi> who told her that ſhe was very Sick, and that her Father and Mother were alſo very Sick, that they were a Bed aſleep. This Informant departed, and came again the next Morning, and this Informant then meeting with the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Pengelley,</hi> ſhe asked her how her Father and Mother did, who told her that they were very ill, and deſired this Informant to go up in the Chamber and ſee them: And when this Informant came into the Chamber, ſhe found the ſaid Maſter <hi>Weeks</hi> his Wife very ill, with Vomiting and Purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and ſhe demanded of them what they had eaten the day before: They ſaid, nothing but Pottage; And this Informant further ſaith, that ſhe coming into the Court of the ſaid Maſter <hi>Weekes,</hi> ſhe ſaw Vomiting there which the Dog had done, whereupon ſhe deſired them to take ſome Oyl and Sack, which was taken by Maſter <hi>Weeks</hi> and his Daughter <hi>Pengelley,</hi> but his Wife did take very little, and that the Nurſe and Child took ſome Sack and Oyl likewiſe. And this Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant further ſaith, that the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Weeks</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſo bad till about Three of the Clock in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon, and then died: And endeavoring to find out the cauſe, the next day they put a Spoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of the ſame<note n="*" place="margin">Oatmeal.</note> Girts which were in the Pottage, and boyled it in a Pint of Water, and gave the ſame to the Dog. And about half an hour after, the Dog was taken with Vomitings, and looking into the bottom of the Skillet wherein the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96502:11"/>Water and Girts were boyled, took out ſome Yellow thing, which they underſtood to be Yellow <hi>Arſenick;</hi> to make a further diſovery, they took the remainder of the<note n="*" place="margin">Oatmeal.</note> Girts, and put them in a Bowl of Water, intending to ſee what was therein, to ſtand a little white, and when they came to ſee for it, the<note n="*" place="margin">Oatmeal.</note> Girts were taken out, and the Water thrown away by <hi>Anne Evans</hi> (Apprentice to the ſaid <hi>William Weeks</hi> Dyer) into the Sink; and ſeeing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards into the Sink, they took up ſome more of the Poyſon, and ſhewed it to Doctor <hi>Holland,</hi> and ſome other Phyſitians, who ſaid it was Yellow <hi>Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Mary Hurd.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="information">
            <head>The Information of <hi>Hugh Littleworth,</hi> taken before the Right Worſhipful <hi>William Weeks</hi> Major of <hi>Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth.</hi> Auguſt <hi>25. 1675.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe ſaid Informant faith, that he having ſome diſcourſe with <hi>Anne Evans,</hi> ſhe ſaid, that there had been a difference between the Nurſe <hi>Philip</hi> Wife of <hi>Richard Cary</hi> and her Miſtris <hi>Weeks,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Philip Cary</hi> ſaid, that ſhe would fit her Miſtris, and the ſaid <hi>Philip Cary</hi> asking of the ſaid <hi>Evans</hi> where ſhe ſhould have any <hi>Rats-bane.</hi> Who replied, if ſhe did go to the Apothecary, he would take her name. And alſo the ſaid <hi>Evans</hi> confeſſed to this Informant, that ſhe gathering of Herbs on Wedneſday or Thurſday laſt in the Garden, ſome Stones were thrown in over the Wall into the Garden, and at laſt a Paper was thrown in, which ſhe took up and carried it in, and put it in a Salt-Sellar, ſhewing it to the ſaid <hi>Philip Cary,</hi> who told her that ſhe did not know what it was, and then
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96502:11"/>ſhe put it into the Salt-Sellar again, and ſeeking for it on Sabbath day at night, it was gone out of the Salt-Sellar. And this Informant further ſaith, that he was informed by <hi>Chriſtopher Scibbow,</hi> that the ſaid <hi>Philip Cary</hi> was packing up her Cloaths to be gon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hugh Littleworth.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elizabeth Crone</hi> and <hi>Anne Partridge</hi> both depoſe the ſame.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="information">
            <head>The Information of the ſaid <hi>Philip Cary</hi> taken as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</head>
            <p>THe ſaid Informant ſaith, that on Munday was Sevennight, there was a difference between her and her Miſtris concerning the Frying of Pilchards, and amongſt other things, the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Weeks</hi> call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Informant Whore, and ſaid, that ſhe was her Husbands Whore. And this Informant told the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Weeks,</hi> that ſhe had made a difference between this Informant and her Husband; but the next Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Weeks</hi> and this Informant were very good Friends; and this Informant going to call her Husband where he was at Keels, he took up a Bowl in his Hand, and ſaid, that ſhe ſhould go home to Maſter <hi>Weeks,</hi> for that ſhe was his Whore. And this Informant further ſaith, that this Informant and her Husband being invited to Dinner to the ſaid Maſter <hi>Weeks</hi> his Houſe on Sabbath day laſt, and when ſhe came, there was a Diſh of Pottage laded up before ſhe came, which ſhe did eat, and her Husband did eat two Diſhes of the ſame Pottage.</p>
            <p>And this Informant further ſaith, that Miſtris <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelley</hi> did tell this Informant, that <hi>Anne Evans</hi> did
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96502:12"/>riſe on Sabbath day by Four of the Clock in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which ſhe did wonder at, and this Informant fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, that the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> told her, that ſhe would go away with the Mountebanks, for ſhe could not indure the hardneſs of her Miſtris.</p>
            <p>And this Informant further ſaith, that the Munday following, ſhe Vomited and Purged, and that ſhe had great pains in her Stomack, and Griping in the Guts, and alſo ſaith, that there are no retainers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Houſe beſides this Informant, and the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans,</hi> and that no one elſe doth dreſs the Meat.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="examination">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Anne Evans,</hi> taken as aforeſaid on Oath the 26th. of <hi>Auguſt, 1675.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe ſaid Examinant ſaith, that about a Fourt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night or Three Weeks ſince, there then being a difference between her Miſtris <hi>Elizabeth Weeks,</hi> and Nurſe <hi>Philip Cary,</hi> the ſaid Nurſe ſaid, that ſhe would fit her one way or other. And this Informant further ſaith, that a Tueſday laſt, ſhe going out into the Garden to gather Herbs, amongſt the Mary golds ſhe found a Paper, in which was a yellow Stone, which ſhe thought was Painting, but now ſhe ſuppoſeth it was <hi>Rats-bane,</hi> ſo this Informant carried it in, and put it in a Salt-Sellar, and a Saturday ſhe ſhewed the ſame to the Nurſe, and asked her what it was, who told her ſhe knew not, and then ſhe put it in the Salt. Sellar again.</p>
            <p>And this Examinant further ſaith, that the next day after the ſaid difference, the ſaid Nurſe told this Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant, ſhe did wiſh the old <hi>Gypſon</hi> were ſo far as ſhe did wiſh her, and ſaid that ſhe would fit her, and this Examinant asking her how, ſhe anſwered, a little
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96502:12"/>
               <hi>Rats-bane</hi> would make work with her by and by. And this Examinant asking her where ſhe would have it, ſhe ſaid that there was enough at the Apothecaries. And this Examinant told her, that he would take her name, and ſhe anſwered, that there was an Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary in St. <hi>Andrews Street</hi> that did not know her.</p>
            <p>And this Examinant further ſaith, that on Saturday laſt, this Examinant fetched a Pot of Beer for her Maſter before he went to <hi>Plympton,</hi> and her Maſter made a Toaſt, and put in Nutmeg and Sugar therein, and did Drink thereof, and her Miſtris, and Miſtris <hi>Pengelley,</hi> and her Son <hi>John,</hi> and put the remainder in the Window, and when this Examinant came to ſee for the Drink, there was a great Spider in it, then ſhe took out the Spider with a Spoon, and left in the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and a little after ſhe asking the Nurſe whether ſhe had drank the Beer that ſtood in the Window, ſhe ſaid no. Then this Examinant told her that there was a Spider in it, but ſhe had taken it out, and did believe that her Miſtris had drank it; then the Nurſe replied, thou ſhouldeſt have let it alone thou Fool, and not have taken it out, but ſhouldeſt have ſquatted it abroad in the Beer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The Sign of <hi>Anne</hi> A.E. <hi>Evans.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="examination">
            <head>The Examination of the ſaid <hi>Philip Cary,</hi> taken as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</head>
            <p>THe ſaid Examinant being demanded whether ſhe did ſay that ſhe did wiſh the old <hi>Gypſon</hi> were ſo far as ſhe did wiſh, and that ſhe would fit her, and whether ſhe did ſay that her <hi>Rats-bane</hi> would work with her by and by, of words to that effect, ſhe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, no. And being demanded whether ſhe had
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96502:13"/>any diſcourſe with the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> touching the Spider on Saturday laſt, which ſhould be taken out of the Beer, ſhe ſaith ſhe had; and being demanded why ſhe ſaid to the ſaid <hi>Evans,</hi> that ſhe ſhould have let the Spider alone and ſquatted it abroad in the Beer, or uſed any words to that effect, ſhe ſaith, that ſhe had no diſcourſe with her, nor ſpake any ſuch thing; and this Examinant further ſaith, that ſhe did hear the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> ſay, that ſhe would make away with her Miſtris, to wit, the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Weeks,</hi> there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a difference between them on Saturday was Fourt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, to the beſt of this Examinants remembrance: and being demanded why ſhe did not reveal it, ſhe anſwered, that the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> did deſire her that ſhe would not reveal it, for if ſhe did, ſhe ſhould be even killed, and therefore ſhe did forbear to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The Sign of the ſaid <hi>Philip Cary.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="examination">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Anne Evans,</hi> taken before the Right Worſhipful. <hi>William Weeks</hi> Major, and <hi>William Jennings</hi> Merchant, two Juſtices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Firſt day of <hi>September 1675.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe ſaid Examinant ſaith, that there hath been a continual difference between the ſaid Nurſe <hi>Philip Cary,</hi> and her Miſtris <hi>Elizabeth Weeks,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Philip Cary</hi> did ſay ſeveral times, that ſhe would fit the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Weeks.</hi> And this Examinant further ſaith, that yeſterday was Fourtnight, ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Herb Garden, there were ſome Stones thrown into the Herb Garden by ſome Children which were out in the Lane, and ſhe looking out over the Wall, ſaw the ſaid <hi>Philip Cary</hi> and the Child out in the Lane. And this Examinant further ſaith, that ſhe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96502:13"/>then took up a Paper, in which was a yellow Stone, which ſhe thought was yellow Painting, but now ſhe doth think that it was <hi>Rats-bane,</hi> ſo this Examinant carried it in, and put it in a Salt-Sellar, and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday following, this Examinant cleanſing of the Shelves, ſhe took it down, and put it in her Pocket, and in the Evening ſhe ſhewed it to the Nurſe, and asked her what it was, who ſeeming not to take notice of it, ſhe (this Examinant) put it again in the Salt-Sellar, ſo ſhe went out unto the Conduit to fetch ſome Water, and when ſhe came in again, this Examinant further ſaith, that ſhe doth believe, that the ſaid Nurſe did take down the ſaid <hi>Rats-bane,</hi> for that when ſhe came in, ſhe ſaw the ſaid Nurſe breaking of it between two Tiles into Powder, and this Examinant asking her what ſhe would do with it when ſhe had broken it, ſhe replied, ſhe was going to fit a Medicine for the old Woman, meaning the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Weeks,</hi> and then the ſaid Nurſe, when ſhe had broken the ſame ſmall, ſhe took ſome of the ſame <hi>Rats bane</hi> and put it in a Cloam-Diſh, and then drew about a quarter of a Pint of Small Beer to it, and ſo let it ſteep all night long: And then the ſaid Nurſe gave ſome of the ſaid <hi>Rats-bane</hi> to this Informant, and told her that ſhe ſhould put the ſame into the Old womans Diſh, when ſhe did take up ſome Pottage for her, and you ſhall ſee, as ſhe ſaid, what ſport we ſhall have with her to Morrow, and that which this Examinant ſhould give her, would do her no hurt, but that which ſhe had fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted would do her work, and that it would make her die within half an hour, and ſaid, when the Old wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was gone, that we ſhould live ſo merry as the days were long. And this Examinant further ſaith, that the ſaid Nurſe did charge this Examinant upon her life, that ſhe ſhould not tell of it, for unleſs that ſhe this Examinant did not declare it, it would never
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96502:14"/>come to light: And withal, told this Examinant, that if ſhe did tell of it, ſhe would deny it, and lay it all upon this Examinant. And this Examinant fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, that the next day being Sunday, having Boiled a piece of Beef, and part of a Neck of Veal and Cabbidge, and Carrots, and made Pottage; And then about Eleven of the Clock, the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Weeks</hi> asked for a Diſh of Pottage, and bid this Examinant lade up a Diſh, which this Examinant did, and then put in the ſaid <hi>Rats-bane</hi> into the Diſh, according as the Nurſe had ordered, thinking of no hurt; and this Examinant ſaith, that the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Weeks</hi> did eat up all the Pottage, and left the Bread in the Diſh, and then ſhe laded up more Pottage to the Bread in the ſame Diſh, and the ſaid Maſter <hi>Weeks</hi> did eat up all the Pottage, and very little Bread: and then Miſtris <hi>Marry Pengelley</hi> laded up ſome more Pottage to the ſame Bread, in the ſame Diſh, which ſhe did then eat up all, Pottage and Bread. And this Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant ſaith, that about three hours after the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Weeks</hi> was taken with Purging and Vomiting, and being very dry, they gave this Examinant order to fetch a Pot of Strong Beer in a Silver Tankard, and the mean while the ſaid Nurſe made a Toſt to put in it, which ſhe accordingly fetcht, and when ſhe came into the Kitchin, where the ſaid Nurſe was making of a Toaſt, ſhe gave the Tankard with the Beer unto the Nurſe: And this Examinant ſaith, that ſhe did ſee the ſaid Nurſe Drink a little of the Beer, which was in the ſaid Tankard, and then preſently filled it up again with the ſame Beer, in which the ſaid <hi>Rats-bane</hi> was ſteeped in the night before, and then the ſaid Nurſe carried the ſame Beer up in the Chamber unto the ſaid Maſter <hi>Weeks</hi> and Miſtris <hi>Weeks:</hi> And this Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant going up after her with a Swab to take up the Vomiting. This Examinant ſaw the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Weeks</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96502:14"/>Drink firſt of the ſaid Beer, and then ſhe delivered it to Maſter <hi>Weeks,</hi> and he did Drink, ſo he delivered it to Miſtris <hi>Pengelley,</hi> and ſhe found fault with it, and ſaid, that the Beer was keamy, and that if they had no better, they ſhould fetch it at ſome other place. But this Examinant did ſee the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Pengelley</hi> eat ſome of the ſaid Toaſt: And this Examinant fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, having the next day an occaſion to make uſe of the ſaid Tankard, found the inſide thereof in the bottom, black, yellow, and diſcolored, as though it was Cankered, and the Nurſe bad her Scour it out with Sand, whereas before when ſhe fetcht the Beer it was clean.</p>
            <p>And this Examinant further ſaith, that ſhe being troubled to ſee her Maſter and Miſtris ſo Sick; ſhe ſaid, Alas! Nurſe, what have you done, that our Maſter and Miſtris are ſo very Sick? She replied, what ſhe had done as to Miſtris <hi>Weeks,</hi> ſhe had done God good Service in it, to rid her out of the way, and hoped that ſhe had done her buſineſs, and did look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, that ſhe had done no ſin in it; and ſaith, as to the Girts that ſhe can ſay no farther, but what ſhe hath ſaid in her former Examination; to which for more certainty ſhe referreth her ſelf.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The Mark of the ſaid <hi>Anne</hi> A. E. <hi>Evans.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="examination">
            <head>The Examination of the ſaid <hi>Philip Cary,</hi> taken as aforeſaid.</head>
            <p>THe ſaid Examinant being demanded whether the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> did not ſhow her the ſaid yellow Stone, on Saturday laſt was Sevennight, and whether ſhe did not break it abroad in Powder between two Tiles, and whether ſhe did not ſteep part of it in a Diſh in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96502:15"/>Small Beer, and whether ſhe did not give ſome of the ſame <hi>Rats-bane</hi> which ſhe had broken unto the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans,</hi> and told her that ſhe ſhould put it into the Old womans Diſh, meaning the Old Miſtris <hi>Weeks,</hi> or uſed any words to that effect, anſwered, No. And being demanded alſo, whether ſhe had any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans,</hi> concerning the Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon mentioned in the aforeſaid Examination of the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans,</hi> or any words to that effect, denies the ſame; but ſaith, that ſhe doth believe that they ſhall both die for it, becauſe ſhe hath concealed the Counſel of the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The Mark of <hi>Philip</hi> † <hi>Cary.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="narrative">
            <p>ANd now they are in ſafe Cuſtody, in the Priſon joyning to the Town-Hall in <hi>Plymouth,</hi> where they have time and leiſure to ruminate upon their foul and odious Crime, to conſider of the horrible danger to which theſe pretious Souls are expoſed, and to make their Peace with God, if it be well husbanded and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved. But I fear me, that though the Lord wait graciouſly Six Months together for their Repentance, and cry aloud by this terrible diſpenſation to convert, reform and give Glory to him before they come to Judgment, we ſhall even after their Condemnation at the Aſſizes, meet with other and worſe news from them. Before we talk with theſe Malefactors any further, it will not be unneceſſary to make a little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, and ſee what evidence the Righteous Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God doth Adminiſter towards a fuller dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their Sin and Guilt.</p>
            <p>Miſtris <hi>Weeks</hi> being deceaſed, and Doctor <hi>Holland</hi> a Phyſitian of the Town having averred it to be by Poyſon; the Coronor was ſent for, to inquire into the cauſes of her death; who having impannel'd his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96502:15"/>Jury, and examined Witneſſes, do all Unanimouſly concurre in their Verdict, that ſhe was murdered, and that by Poyſon.</p>
            <p>The ſame Verdict alſo was given in by another Jury, that ſate upon the death of Miſtris <hi>Pengelley.</hi> The obſtinacy of the Nurſe to the very inſtant of her going off the Ladder, in denying her ſelf either princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal or acceſſary to this bloody fact, will excuſe the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, if he ſubjoyn the reſpective depoſitions of ſeveral Witneſſes upon their Oath concerning it, that ſo the Juſtice of God may be glorified, and no Siniſter thoughts of the Judge, Grand or Petty Juries that condemned her be entertained.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="examination">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Chriſtopher Scibbow</hi> of <hi>Plymouth</hi> in the County of <hi>Devon</hi> Dyer, had and taken at <hi>Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> aforeſaid, by and before <hi>Thomas Payne</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, Coronor for our Soveraign Lord the King, within the Liberty of the <hi>Burrough</hi> of <hi>Plymouth</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, on the Corporal Oath of the ſaid Examinant, this 27th. day of <hi>Auguſt, Anno Domini, 1675.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe ſaid Examinant ſaith, that on Wedneſday night laſt, he was at the Priſon window in <hi>Plymouth,</hi> where <hi>Anne Evans</hi> Spinſter was committed on Suſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for poyſoning <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the wife of <hi>William Weeks</hi> Dyer, when and where this Examinant heard the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> to ſay, that the Nurſe (meaning <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> the wife of <hi>Richard Cary</hi>) did ask of her about a month before to buy ſome <hi>Rats-bane,</hi> and that ſhe gave anſwer to the ſaid Nurſe, that ſhe would not do it, becauſe the Apothecary would put her name upon the Book.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Chriſtopher Scibbow.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="examination">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:96502:16"/>
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Suſanna,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Brian Canſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> of <hi>Plymouth</hi> aforeſaid Planter, taken before the ſaid Coronor, on the Corporal Oath of the ſaid Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, the day and year aforeſaid.</head>
            <p>THe ſaid Examinant ſaith, that on Munday laſt; ſhe went and ſaw <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Wife of <hi>William Weeks</hi> Dyer, and found her very Sick, and this Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant, and other Perſons that were preſent, did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that ſhe had been poyſoned, upon which there was ſome new Broth made, and made with ſome of the ſame<note n="*" place="margin">Oatmeal.</note> Girts, that had been put into the old Broth, and when it was made, ſhe gave it to a great Dog, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently Vomited it up again. She alſo ſaith, that <hi>Anne Evans,</hi> Maſter <hi>Weeks</hi> his Servant, ſhewed this Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant the bottom of the new Broth, where was ſound a Yellow Gravel, and one ſhewing of it to Miſtris <hi>Hurd</hi> and others, they did believe that it was <hi>Rats-bane.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Suſanna Cansfield.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="examination">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Alice,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Anthony Windeit</hi> of <hi>Plymouth,</hi> aforeſaid Clothier, taken as aforeſaid before the ſaid Coronor on her Oath.</head>
            <p>THe ſaid Examinant ſaith, that on Wedneſday laſt, ſhe went and ſaw Maſter <hi>William Weeks Dyer,</hi> and <hi>Mary Pengelley,</hi> being very Sick, it being reported that they and Miſtris <hi>Weeks</hi> had been poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, on which it was ſaid, that the<note n="*" place="margin">Oatmeal.</note> Girts which were in the houſe and had not been uſed, ſhould be waſhed, and the ſame were accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly waſhed by <hi>Anne Evans,</hi> the ſaid Maſter <hi>Weeks</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:96502:16"/>his Servant, and in the bottom there was found ſome Yellow, like Gravel, part whereof was about the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a ſmall Pins head, upon which this Examinant blamed the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> for waſhing the ſame without order, who confeſſed that ſhe had done it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Order.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Alice Windeit.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="examination">
            <head>The Examination and Information of <hi>Mary Pengelley</hi> of <hi>Plymouth,</hi> in the County of <hi>Devon</hi> Widow, taken before the ſaid Coronor on her Corporal Oath, the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of <hi>Auguſt, Anno Domini 1675.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe ſaid Examinant ſaith, that yeſterday laſt was Sevennight in the Morning, <hi>Anne Evans</hi> the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice of Maſter <hi>William Weeks</hi> Dyer, fetched a Tankard of Strong Beer, on which there ſeemed unto this Examinant that there was Keam, for which ſhe was blamed, of which this Examinant drank hearty: And now this Examinant doth verily believe by what hath happened ſince, that that which ſhe took to be Keam on the ſaid Beer, was Poyſon: And this Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant further ſaith, that afterwards yeſterday was Sevennight ſhe being come down over the Staires in the Kitchin, about Noon the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> asked this Examinant if ſhe would eat any Pottage, (the ſaid <hi>William Weeks</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his Wife, this Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minants Father and Mother having eaten Pottage a little before,) and this Examinant told her that ſhe would, and accordingly ſhe did eat a Diſh of Pottage, (being out of the ſame Diſh that her ſaid Father and Mother did ſo eat Pottage a little before,) and that preſently after this Examinant and her ſaid Father and Mother were taken exceeding Sick, of which her ſaid Mother died the next day after. And this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminant
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96502:17"/>doth verily believe in her Conſcience, that the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> with the contrivance of <hi>Philip</hi> the Wife of <hi>Richard Cary,</hi> who alſo lived in the ſaid Maſter <hi>Weeks</hi> his Houſe, did put Poyſon in the ſaid Pottage, and ſo poyſoned her ſaid Mother, whereof ſhe died, and alſo poyſoned her ſaid Father and this Examinant. And this Examinant doth alſo believe that the ſaid <hi>Richard Cary,</hi> who fetched his Diet in the ſaid houſe, had alſo ſome hand in the ſaid contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signum praedictae <hi>Mariae Pengelley.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="examination">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>William Weeks</hi> of <hi>Plymouth</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Dyer, on his Corporal Oath before the ſaid Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, the Thirtieth day of <hi>Auguſt, 1675.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe ſaid Examinant ſaith, that there have been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſeveral differences between <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minants Wife, and <hi>Anne Evans</hi> his Apprentice, and <hi>Philip</hi> the Wife of <hi>Richard Cary</hi> his Servant; and that yeſterday was Sevennight laſt, about Noon, the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> took up a Diſh of Pottage, and gave the ſame to this Examinants Wife, who did eat up moſt part of the Broth, but did eat up little or nothing of the Bread, ſhe not liking the ſame; and one looking into the Diſh, this Examinant found ſome Yellow Gravel (and by what this Examinant doth under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſince, he verily believes that it was Yellow <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenick.</hi>) And he demanding what it was, there was no one there would or could make any diſcovery. And preſently afterwards the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> took up ſome more Pottage in the ſaid Diſh; to the Bread which his Wife had left, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d he did eat up the Broth thereof, and ſome of the ſaid Gravel which cruſhed in his Teeth, but did not eat any of the Fleſh which was
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96502:17"/>boiled in the ſaid Pottage, for that it did look black: And preſently after <hi>Mary Pengelley</hi> Widow, this Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minants Daughter did eat ſome of the ſame Pottage, and all Three were preſently taken very Sick by great Swellings and Vomitings, and that his ſaid Wife con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſo till the next day and died. And this Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant doth verily believe in his Conſcience, that the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans,</hi> together with the ſaid <hi>Philip Cary,</hi> did wittingly and willingly put <hi>Arſenick</hi> into the ſaid Pottage, and ſo poyſoned his ſaid Wife, whereof ſhe died. And this Examinant alſo doth verily believe in his Conſcience, that the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> and <hi>Philip Cary,</hi> did by the ſame means and procurement as aforeſaid, Poyſon this Examinant and the ſaid <hi>Mary Pengelley.</hi> And he doth alſo verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that the ſaid <hi>Richard Cary</hi> was privy and had a hand therein.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Per me <hi>William Weeks.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="examination">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Philip Sendy</hi> of <hi>Plymouth</hi> aforeſaid, Widow, taken before the ſaid Coronor on her Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Oath, the Two and twentieth day of <hi>September, Anno Domini 1675.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe ſaid Examinant ſaith, that the day on which Miſtris <hi>Elizabeth Weeks</hi> was Buried, <hi>Philip</hi> the Wife of <hi>Richard Cary</hi> being then in <hi>Plymouth</hi> Priſon on Suſpition, for poyſoning of the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Weeks;</hi> ſhe the ſaid <hi>Philip</hi> ſent for this Examinant, to whom this Examinant went, and ſpoke with her, and demanded of her what ſhe would have, who made anſwer, that this Examinant ſhould remember her Service to her Maſter and Miſtris, and to tell them that ſhe was troubled that ſhe had not acquainted her, what ſhe (meaning as this Examinant believeth one <hi>Anne
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96502:18"/>Evans</hi>) had an intent to do the Saturday was Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night before.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signum praedictae P <hi>Philip Sendy.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="examination">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Joane</hi> the Wife of <hi>Richard Scannel</hi> of <hi>Plymouth</hi> aforeſaid Cooper, taken before the ſaid Coronor on her Corporal Oath, the day and year laſt mentioned.</head>
            <p>THe ſaid Examinant ſaith, that the Munday Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Wife of <hi>William Weeks</hi> died, being the Three and twentieth day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, this Examinant coming into the Kitchin of the ſaid Maſter <hi>Weeks,</hi> where was <hi>Anne Evans, Richard Cary,</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> his wife, unto whom this Examinant ſpoke, that it was very ſad there ſhould be ſo many Sick, upon which the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> ſaid, that ſhe was forry for her Miſtris (meaning <hi>Mary Pengelley,</hi>) but was glad that the Old Devil was gone (meaning that the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Weeks</hi> was dead) and ſaid that ſhe would ſing the day that ſhe was Buried, but would not lye one night in the houſe after ſhe was Buried, for that ſhe was ſure ſhe would appear again as a Spirit, and that the Devil had been a long time building of a Pallace for her, and that the yeſterday before he had laid the laſt Stone, and that that very day he placed her in. All which was ſpoken by the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans,</hi> in the preſence and hearing of the ſaid <hi>Richard Cary,</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> his wife, and although this Examinant did blame the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans,</hi> yet they, nor either of them did any way reprove the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> for what ſhe did ſay.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joane Scannel.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="examination">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:96502:18"/>
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Joane</hi> the Wiſe of <hi>William How</hi> of <hi>Plymouth</hi> aforeſaid Beer-Brewer, taken before the ſaid Coronor on her Corporal Oath, the day and year laſt mentioned.</head>
            <p>THe ſaid Examinant ſaith, that the very day that <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the wife of <hi>William Weeks</hi> Dyer died, being the Three and twentieth day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt paſt, this Examinant being at the houſe of the ſaid <hi>William Weeks,</hi> and diſcourſing with <hi>Philip</hi> the wife of <hi>Richard Cary,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Philip Cary</hi> went away from this Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant, and ſaid, Oh that ſhe ſhould ever go out the Saturday before (to the beſt of this Examinants re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance) to ruine this Family (meaning the ſaid Maſter <hi>Weeks</hi> his Family.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joane How.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="examination">
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Arabella</hi> the Wife of <hi>Thomas Moore</hi> of <hi>Plymouth,</hi> aforeſaid Merchant, taken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid Coronor on her Corporal Oath, the day and year laſt mentioned.</head>
            <p>THe ſaid Examinant ſaith, that the day that <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> the wife of <hi>William Weeks</hi> died, or the day after, ſhe being at the houſe of the ſaid <hi>William Weeks, Philip</hi> the wife of <hi>Richard Cary</hi> wept, and wrung her hands, and ſaid to this Examinant, Oh Miſtris <hi>Moore,</hi> that ever ſhe ſhould go out of Doors to ruine this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily! (Meaning the ſaid Maſter <hi>Weeks</hi> his Family.)</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Arabella Moore.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marian Cook worthy</hi> of <hi>Plymouth</hi> Spinſter, being then ſworn, depoſeth the ſame.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="examination">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:96502:19"/>
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Philip</hi> the Wiſe of <hi>Richard Cary</hi> of <hi>Plymouth,</hi> aforeſaid Husbandman, taken before the ſaid Coronor, the day and year aforeſaid, laſt menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned.</head>
            <p>THe ſaid Examinant being demanded whether ſhe were a Servant at Wages to <hi>Mary Pengelley,</hi> late of <hi>Plymouth,</hi> aforeſaid Widow deceaſed, at the time of the death of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the wife of <hi>William Weeks;</hi> she ſaith that she was then a Servant to the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Pengelley</hi> at Wages, and continued in the ſame Service until ſhe was committed to Priſon; she alſo ſaith, that when ſhe was a Nurſe unto the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Pengelley,</hi> she had Three Pound and Ten Shillings <hi>per annum,</hi> and that the ſame was continued to her ever ſince, and she believeth that there is Money now due to her.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signum praedictae, <hi>Philip</hi> † <hi>Cary.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="narrative">
            <p>THe Witneſſes having been Examined, their Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions taken, they are all bound over to Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute our Malefactors at the next Aſſizes for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Devon,</hi> whoſe Mittimus is now Signed and Seal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and they ſent to the High Goal near the Caſtle of <hi>Exon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here they ſpend full Six Months, but what! In a ſerious and ſad reflection upon their hainous and Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſin: In the exerciſes of Repentance, Contrition, and Godlineſs: No, in nothing leſs than in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of ſuch indiſpenſible Duties.</p>
            <p>In truth they came thither the Slaves and Vaſſals of the Devil, full of Ignorance, and unacquainted with God, and the things of God, they were got into a Priſon, <hi>the very Suburbs of Hell,</hi> a place (to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96502:19"/>knowledge) <hi>a Seminary of all Villanies, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs, and Impieties; deſtitute of good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, good Books, and the good means of Grace, and of all helps, ſaving their Affliction, that might lead them Heaven-ward.</hi> And it was very improbable, that under ſo great a want of Spiritual advantages, they ſhould bethink themſelves of Heaven and Eternity. Indeed they might and ought to have done it. But they were captivated by the Prince of Darkneſs, who had blinded the eyes of their underſtandings, and Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their hearts as with an hot Iron, that they ſhould not ſee, nor know, nor conſider the things that belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto their Peace. Beſides they were held in ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Chains than thoſe of Iron; their own iniquities had taken hold of them, and they were bound with the Cords of their ſins.</p>
            <p>Here they fed themſelves, and are flattered alſo by their Companions in Ungodlineſs, with the fond and falſe hopes of eſcaping the Juſtice of man; and as for that of God, they never Dream of it, it enters not into their thoughts. Let them but eſcape the Gallows and get out of Goal, they imagine Hell may be avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with leſs difficulty, and Heaven obtained with far more facility.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Camelion-like</hi> they live upon the Air, or with <hi>Ephraim</hi> upon the Eaſt wind; or as <hi>Eſay's</hi> Idolator they feed upon Aſhes; a deceived heart hath turned them aſide, that they cannot deliver their Souls, nor ſay, is there not a lie in our right hands? But in the depth of their Senceleſneſs and Security, they are ſurprized with a cold damp.</p>
            <p>The Aſſizes are come, the Judges arrived, the Trumpets ſound, and our wretched Priſoners are Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned unto Judgment. Up they go unto the Bar with heavy hearts, though with undejected Countenances. They had ſome Figleave excuſes to cover their ſhame,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96502:20"/>and rather than want a Shift and Plea for themſelves, they will add ſin to ſin, lyings and impudent denials. Alas! Poor Souls, this is not to leſſen, but to aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate your guilt, this doth not hide but diſcover it. You Cloath your ſelves with a Net, your Nakedneſs and filth is the more Apparent. Witneſſes are exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, evidence is produced, the Malefactors are heard and permitted to ſpeak for themſelves, the Bill was found, and an Impartial Jury declares them Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they are caſt, Sentence is pronounced, and now being dead in Law, they Petition for a Tranſportation.</p>
            <p>Here is the laſt Refuge of miſerable Murderers; But Juſtice diſpenſeth no favors, they may be Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to another world, not to another Land. Blood cries for Blood. Innocent Blood demandeth Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. God hath ſaid it, and the Righteous Law of <hi>England</hi> hath confirmed it; that he, who ſheddeth mans Blood, by man ſhall his Blood be ſhed, a man that offers Violence to the blood of any perſon, ſhall flie to the Pit, let no man ſtay him.</p>
            <p>Accordingly their Petition is rejected, their Requeſt is denied, they are bidden to prepare for death, all hopes of life here have left and forſaken them.</p>
            <p>The Girl, as Guilty of Petty Treaſon and Murder, is Sentenced to be drawn on an Hurdle to the place where ſhe ſhall be Executed, and there Burnt to death. An horrible death! An Emblem and lively Picture of Hell torments! D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>awn as if dragged by Devils, Burnt alive, as if in that Lake of Fire and Brimſtone already! Lord! what Rocks are theſe that do not rend and break to pieces at the hearing and thinking of it? Methinks the very Sentence ſhould have ſtruck her dead. There is ſo much of horror in it, that with Nabal her Heart ſhould have died in her. Yet ſhe lives under it. Lord! Let it be in mercy to her! Space is given her to eſcape the wrath of God, though
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96502:20"/>ſhe cannot the vengeance of Man. The Nurſe muſt Hang till ſhe be dead, a too gentle death for ſuch a <hi>Prodigy of Ungodlineſs!</hi> She Pleads ſtifly her Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, diſowns all Guilt, takes no Shame, her Brow is Braſs, ſhe is Impudent, and hath an Whores Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head. If ever there were a Daughter of Hell, this was one in her proper colors. No evidence ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince her. Confeſs faith ſhe! Then I ſhall Hang in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, I deny the fact, none ſaw it, none knew it but the Girl, it may be that vile Perſon her Husband, had a Finger in it, but he is gone. Some will pitty me, though none will believe me, none can help me. Yet though ſhe muſt die, as ſure as ſhe was born, the Devil helps her to one Expedient, as ſhe conceives that may ſave her Life. My Lord, I am Innocent, I am with Child, do not kill two Innocents. If I muſt die, let my Child live!</p>
            <p>The Reverend Judge is too Righteous to puniſh the Innocent with the Guilty; or to deſtroy the Child for the Mothers fault. Hence a Midwife is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to attend the Court, a Jury of Matrons impannell'd, the Murdereſs is ſearched, and after their ſtricteſt Scrutiny and Inqueſt, they find her a Lyar, to have troubled the Court needleſly, ſhe is not quick, as ſhe would bear them in hand, if ſhe have at all conceived.</p>
            <p>Upon this they are returned to their Priſons, and now in ſight of Hell. Others pitty them, and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at their diſmal State; but poor wretches, they have no Bowels for themſelves, yea, without any gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Sentiments, without any feeling apprehenſions of their approaching miſery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plymouth</hi> hath been the firſt Scene of this Tragedy, there had they committed their Murders, and upon the humble Petition of Maſter <hi>Weeks,</hi> Husband, and Father to the Murdered Perſons, and concurrent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96502:21"/>of the Grand Jury, His Lordſhip grants it to be the place of their Execution. This was a rare Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, ſuch a ſight was never ſeen ſince the foundations of that Town. Oh! that it might be the laſt.</p>
            <p>In the Interval of their Sentence and Execution, ſeveral Divines viſit them.</p>
            <p>The Right Reverend Dioceſan, out of his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous care of their happineſs, ordered two, who fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently attended on them, but with no ſucceſs on the Nurſes part. Other Miniſters moved by Charity, and yearning at their miſery, did concur to uſe their utmoſt endeavors to ſave them from Hell. Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Exhortations, Prayers, Tears, dreadful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciations of unſuſterable torments with the damned, ſweet and gratious promiſes in caſe of Confeſſion, Repentance towards God, and Faith in our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus are uſed and urged with the greateſt Vehemency, and induſtry upon the Nurſe; but they beat the Air, they Plow the Rock, they do her no good, their labor of love is loſt, their Prayers return into their own boſoms.</p>
            <p>The Relator having viſited them ſeveral times while they were in the High Goal at <hi>Exon,</hi> thought it convenient to ſubjoyn the ſubſtance and effect of his conferences with them. Poſſibly it may not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing unto his Reader. Coming into the Priſon early in the Morning, he had the Four condemned Perſons brought unto him; and beſpeaks them in theſe words, <hi>Miſcrable Souls!</hi> I am heartily ſorty to ſee you in this place, and to find you in this Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. You are here Judged of man, and you muſt die; but what alſo if you are Condemned of God, and muſt to Hell for ever? You are Sinners, are you not? You are Guilty of thoſe Crimes for which Sentence is paſt upon you? Three had ſo much Ingenuity as with Weeping and Trembling to acknowledge it.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96502:21"/>Alas! Poor wretches, you are weeping becauſe you have offended man, and brought your ſelves to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Ah! what a mercy would it be, if you could weep unfeignedly for your offences againſt God, and becauſe you have loſt his Image and favor, which is the greateſt Bleſſing, and deſerved his wrath and Curſe, which is the greateſt miſery.</p>
            <p>What think you of Sin? Is it as ſweet and pleaſing to you now you muſt die for it, as when at firſt you did commit it? <hi>Here they were ſilent and Confounded.</hi> Ah! Now you ſee what it is, not to believe God ſpeaking to you from his Word, and by his Miniſters, you were told that ſin would bring ſorrow and ſhame, wrath and death, ſooner or later. The Devil and your own corrupted heart, roſe up againſt this Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of his will, and you made light and ſlight of it, and what have you got by it ? All the Fruit of your ſin is, that you are aſhamed of it, and grieved for it; its wages is the loſs of Earth, Life, and Heaven, and theſe you are expecting every moment. Man hath caſt you off for your ſins; you cannot ſtand before your earthly Judge: And if God ſhall caſt you out of his bleſſed preſence for ever among the Devils and the Damned Spirits, how would you be able to bear it? They being ſomewhat moved, he askt them, How think you to eſcape the dreadful wrath of God? What means have you to ſave your pretious Souls from Hell? What, Firſt do you believe you have Souls to ſave, a being in your Body, that doth not, that cannote die with your Bodies? Do you believe there is a God, and Devil, a Heaven and Hell, and that all the wicked ſhall be turned into Hell, and that you, all of you ſhall be flung into it for your ſins againſt God? At this they ſhrugd up their ſhoulders, and had nothing to anſwer, but their Repentance. Your Repentance, ſaid I, what is that? <hi>Why, our
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96502:22"/>ſorrow for our ſins, we would not commit them again, if they were now undone.</hi> Yea indeed, ſo you ſay, and poſſibly think you would not; but you do not know the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and deceitfulneſs of your own hearts, if you were now as heretofore, and under the ſame temptations. I know nothing to the contrary but that you would be Guilty of the ſame tranſgreſſions, of as bad, or worſe.</p>
            <p>Beſides, ſuppoſe your Repentance were true and real, what amends is that unto God for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold diſhonors you have done him? You have broken every command of God, you are Guilty of innumerable ſins, your very birth and nature is horribly corrupted, and all your life long you have been Rebels againſt God, and you think to put off Gods wrath with your pittiful Repentance, a late Repentance, and it may be no other than the very Reprobates have that are now in Hell.</p>
            <p>Is this all the ſatisfaction you can make to God? <hi>They knew no other;</hi> Then it was told them, that God was a great and terrible God, that would not put up the affronts and wrongs had been done him, without ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, that he would by no means acquit the Guilty. That they had ſinned, and muſt die eternally, and if ever they were redeemed from Eternal wrath, they muſt make God full a mends, and bring him a Ranſome; and if they had none, nor knew where it was to be had, they muſt expect as ſoon as they died, to be damned for ever.</p>
            <p>I asked of them in particular, who or what Jeſus Chriſt was, and what it was he had done for them. To which there was this anſwer made, <hi>they could not tell.</hi> None that knows a Goal will conceive this a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Hardly any but <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> and the moſt ignorant wretches in the whole County are clapt up there; and for one ſin they brought with them into it, they carry away Cart-loads out of it. Our County Priſons being the Common Sinks of the Country, and a Shop
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96502:22"/>wherein all impiety is ſooneſt learned and attained.</p>
            <p>Their ignorance of Chriſt, his Perſon, Natures, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Undertakings for poor Souls, made me to ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate their wickedneſs, and to tell them they had wretchedly miſpent their time, and that now they were going out of the World, they muſt learn the Principles of Chriſtian Religion, and I queſtioned whether they had any Repentance that was pleaſing unto God, for they had no Faith, nor knowledge, even of the moſt neceſſary Truths, without which they could not be ſaved. And for my part I muſt not flatter you, you are nearer Hell than Heaven. Upon this there was a diſcourſe made of Chriſt, adapted to their capacities, as alſo of his wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful love and condeſcenſion in becoming man, and dying for ſinners, and ſatisfying the Juſtice of God, and hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth his death as the price of Redemption unto all Penitent believers; and that this was now offered unto them upon theſe terms of confeſſing and abhorring their ſins, and themſelves for their ſins: and that if they came to God with a ſence and feeling of the inſupportable burden, of the horrid nature, and infinite number of their ſins, and threw themſelves at his feet proſtrate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, imploring his mercy for the paſſion of his dear Son, the Lord would be merciful to them, and he would not caſt them off, but would pardon and forgive their hainous and grievous offences.</p>
            <p>In the cloſe of this conference, Maſter <hi>Holmes</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain to the High Sheriff came into the Chamber, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome words with the Malefactors, we joyntly parted the Priſoners, I withdrawing into another Room with the Nurſe and Maid, and having preſſed them to a free &amp; ingenious confeſſion of their Guilt, the Girl with tears in her eyes gave me for ſubſtance the ſame confeſſion, and not varying in a circumſtance from that which at her firſt apprehenſion ſhe had made unto the Major, and Juſtice of <hi>Plymouth.</hi> I adjured her in the name of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96502:23"/>All-ſeeing and heart-ſearching God, who hated a Lye, and would caſt all Lyars into the Lake of Fire and Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone for ever, to declare nothing but the Truth: That ſhe had ſinned enough already, and had been Guilty of two Murders, and if the Nurſe were Innocent, ſhe ſhould not for a World accuſe her, for if ſhe did, the Lord might Damn her immediately.</p>
            <p>To which ſhe replied with Tears, <hi>Sir, I am a loſt Creature, I have no hopes in this World, I would not willingly Damn my Soul, by drawing upon me the Guilt of more Blood, I ſpeak it as in the preſence of God, I had not put in the Poyſon into the Pottage, had not the Nurſe bid me do it.</hi> And added, <hi>My Body is loſt, but if the Lord would have pitty upon my Soul, it is all that I deſire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the Nurſe hath ſaid, ſhe ſhould never confeſs, though ſhe did Hang for it. That I might confeſs what I would, ſhe would not confeſs any thing.</hi> Upon this I confronted her with <hi>Philip Cary,</hi> ſhe obſtinately denies all, ſtands ſtifly to her Innocency, throws all upon the Girl; ſaith. Judge, Jury, and Witneſſes, are all Guilty of her Innocent Blood, and ſhe will lay it at their Doors. Whereupon, I deſired the Maid to go in to Maſter <hi>Holmes,</hi> and dealt privately with this Vile woman, yet to give Glory unto God by confeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of her ſin, and renouncing all commerce with Hell, that if ſhe did hide her ſin, and keep the Devils Counſel, ſhe could never proſper. That it was in vain for her to think of concealing it, for God knew it, the World knew it, her Country condemned her for it, her own conſcience, if ſhe had any left in her, muſt needs accuſe and condemn her. Poſſibly ſaid I, you think of life, and feed your ſelf with vain imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of eſcaping death, I told her they were fooliſh and groundleſs, that Juſtice would have its Courſe, that the whole World could not ſave her. That ſhe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96502:23"/>was already dead in Law, and muſt be as certainly Executed, as ſhe was already Condemned. That ſhe ſtood upon the brink of the Pit, and was ready to drop down into the bottomleſs Gulph of Hell: That ſhe might, if ſhe would, eſcape it. God offered pardon, Life, Heaven and Salvation to her, provided ſhe would but give glory to him by confeſſing her ſin, and taking the ſhame thereof unto her ſelf. That it was better to do it now than upon the Gallows. She had ſerved the Devil long enough, too too long, and it was a miracle of mercy, if ever the Lord ſhewed mercy to her at laſt; but yet I would, and did aſſure her in his name, (as being his Ambaſſador, and ſent with his Commiſſion to reconcile her unto God, whom ſhe had ſo hainouſly diſhonored,) that if ſhe would diſcloſe all this curſed crime, who firſt contrived it, who man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aged it, and put her upon it, there was hopes. For the Lord was a merciful God unto unfeignd Penitents, and compaſſionated her deplorable condition, and would bring her out of it. That ſhe take care not to Rebel againſt his grace, nor to tear a pardon, that was offered her upon ſuch eaſie terms, in pieces, nor to refuſe Heaven, and all its joys and happineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alas! Sir,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>What will you have me ſay? I will tell you all I know of it. I am as free from this Crime, as the Child that is now Born. But the Maid did it. For ſhe told me ſhe was weary of her life by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of her Miſtris, who was ſuch a Curſt Old Woman, that there was no living with her, and that ſhe was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to leave her Service, and go away with the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanks, and that ſhe told me ſhe would fit her, and had bought the Rats-bane of the Mountebanks Boy or Man, with whom ſhe was in Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was all I could get from her then, and not one Syllable of it true. I told her, ſhe ſhould beware of Lying, and falſe Witneſs bearing, and not let the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96502:24"/>Devil ſit upon her heart and Tongue; and added, when you knew this Girl had an intent to make away her Miſtris, why had not you diſcovered it? She ſaid, <hi>That indeed it was her fault, if it were a fault.</hi> I told her, conſent unto, and concealing of Murder, was Intentional Murder before God and Man, and that ſhe had a real hand in it. <hi>She told me ſhe had none at all, and could give me no other anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our ſecret conference being ended, I brought the Maid again unto her, who avowed her former Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, diſavowed all acquaintance with the Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks Servant, never to have talked with him but once at the Conduit when ſhe fetcht water; and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to her face, that this wicked woman the Nurſe, did oftentimes perſwade her to run away from her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, and if ſhe would have gone away the Saturday before the fact was committed, ſhe would help her to a Riding Suit.</p>
            <p>Unto this ſhe made no reply.</p>
            <p>Returning with them unto Maſter <hi>Holmes,</hi> he preſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon them the evil of their ſin, adviſed them to Repentance: and beſpeaking the Nurſe, <hi>Philip Cary,</hi> ſaid he, there is a report and Suſpition of your having been unclean with your Maſter. At which ſhe fell down upon her Knees in the midſt of us, and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated moſt direfully upon her ſelf, is he ever knew her to be a man or woman, more than by giving ſuck unto his Grand Child.</p>
            <p>Having cleared her Maſter, but not confeſſing any other thing or ſin, Maſter <hi>Holmes</hi> being deſired by me, concluded this conference with Prayer, and we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted.</p>
            <p>In the evening I returned again unto theſe Priſoners, And dealt with the Nurſe to acknowledge her Crime, freely to unboſome her ſelf unto me, that I might ſpread it before the Lord in Prayer, and intreat
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96502:24"/>him for a broken heart, and a new Spirit for her.</p>
            <p>And withdrawing from the Company that crowd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on us into a private Chamber, I deſired her for Gods ſake, her poor Souls ſake, (with cears in my eyes,) that ſhe would yet leave ſin before ſin left her, that ſhe would flee from that wrath to come, that ſhe would bid defiance unto the Devil, who ſhe ſaw had ruined her, and would Damn her everlaſtingly; that ſhe would yet accept of grace and peace, and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with God; it was late indeed to return unto him, but not too late, how ever ſhe muſt not thus dally with the Divine Majeſty, to put him off with delays and lies. That ſhe ſhould not be afraid of ſhame, that it was the greateſt ſhame and reproach unto her to have committed, and concealed this ſin; but it would be a ſtep to Honor and Eternal Glory to confeſs it, good men would then pitty her, pray for her, and God would ſave her.</p>
            <p>And added, that if ſhe would not confeſs it pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blickly to the World, (which yet was her duty, and if ever the Lord gave her Repentance ſhe would do it more feely, and in a more ample manner than I could deſire,) ſhe ſhould at leaſt confeſs it unto me, and I promiſed her upon the word of a Miniſter, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out her conſent I would never divulge it: Or if ſhe would not truſt me with ſuch an important ſecret, I adviſed her to ſingle out ſome Godly Learned Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, or ſome Judicious private Chriſtian, to whom ſhe might Communicate it, and have the benefit of their Aſſiſtance, Counſels, and Directions in order to her Salvation. That it was impoſſible for her to get to Heaven without it. Confeſſion being a main and principal ingredient into Repentance.</p>
            <p>To this ſhe anſwered poſitively ſhe would not, and as peremptorily, that it was enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96502:25"/>to God, and why ſhould ſhe confeſs unto men?</p>
            <p>I told her God required in publick, ſcandalous and crying Crimes, ſuch as thoſe whereof ſhe was Guilty, and eſpecially now the lot of God had attached her, and his holy righteous providence had condemned her, that ſhe ſhould confeſs, accuſe, ſhame and condemn her ſelf publickly. That otherwiſe ſhe ſlandered moſt unworthily the Right Honorable Judge, and the whole Court; and endeavored to raiſe up a baſe and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous ſuſpition of them, as if they had maliciouſly took away her life.</p>
            <p>To which ſhe in plain terms ſaid, <hi>They had, ſhe was Innocent, and they muſt anſwer for it unto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I told her, I heard the Devil ſpeaking with her tongue, and was afraid to ſtay with her any longer, leaſt the ſhould tear her in a Thouſand pieces before me. I had known many hard-hearted Murderers this Thirteen years laſt paſt in this Goal, but never before met with the like; That I ſaw, ſhe was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to be Damned, and go to Hell: And I was ſeriouſly perſwaded, that ſince ſo many Miniſters had been with her, and treated with her about everlaſting life to no purpoſe, and that all my poor endeavors were unſuccesful, that God would never grant her Grace to repent, but that ſhe was a Veſſel of wrath, and preparing her ſelf a pace for endleſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>At theſe words ſhe began to weep, and wept bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, wringing her hands, crying, <hi>Oh! Sir, What ſhall I do? Will you have me ſpeak that which I do not know? I am Innocent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well woman ſaid I, if you be Innocent as to this Crime, tell me, are you not Guilty of ſome other Capital Crime deſerving death? For though the Lord
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:96502:25"/>may ſuffer an Innocent perſon to undergo an unjuſt Sentence from men, yet if he have any Grace, he will own the Juſtice of God in mans injuſtice. It is rare, very rare indeed, that God the Wiſe and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Governor of the World ſuffers the Innocent to be Condemned, and the Guilty abſolved; but if he do, is there not a Cauſe for it? Were I in your Caſe, I would ſay unto the Lord, do not Condemn me, ſhew me wherefore thou contendeſt with me? Come, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rip your heart, and tell me what ſins thou haſt been Guilty of, that though you need no Repentance for this Murder for which as you ſay, you are unjuſtly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, yet you may be holpen unto Repentance for them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir, I know no ſin at all that I am Guilty of,</hi> is her reply. <hi>No Sir, none at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ah! poor wretch, Guilty of no ſin? Is not thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture depraved? Hath not thy life been debauched? How haſt thou improved thy time here in Priſon? In Prayers, Repentance, and preparation for death.</p>
            <p>Still ſhe anſwers, <hi>No ſin deſerving death:</hi> It may be ſhe had committed ſome little ſins as all others do, but for ſins deſerving death, ſhe never had committed any.</p>
            <p>I told her ſhe was a perfect ſtranger to her own heart, that ſhe was full of ſin all over, but blind and could not ſee them; that her little ſins were all dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and as ſhe knew one drop of Poyſon would kill as bad as a Spoonful, ſo one little ſin without Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance would as infallibly Damn her as the greateſt; that for my part I did utterly deſpair of her Salvation, ſeeing the Devil to be ſo ſtrong in her, that ſhe was in the Gall of bitterneſs and bond of Iniquity, and ſeared that ſhe would go to Hell with a lye in her mouth; ſhe was now pleaſing the Devil, and thought
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:96502:26"/>ſhe had found his Service ſo profitable and beneficial to her, that ſhe was reſolved to ſerve him to the laſt, and to hear the <hi>Lord Thunder in her Ears, Go! Thou Curſed Murdereſs into everlaſting Fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At this ſhe wept again, and told me ſhe was a poor<note n="*" place="margin">Ignorant.</note> 
               <hi>Ingrant Soul.</hi> But ſhe hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it would not be ſo bad with her as I ſpake.</p>
            <p>I told her it was my hearts deſire it might not be ſo. I pittied her from my Soul. I labored for her everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing welfare. I had no other deſign upon her than to pluck her out of the Jaws of Hell. That I had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but labor for my pains, and was afraid I ſhould be a Witneſs at the laſt day againſt her for her refuſal, her ſtubborn, wilful rejection of everlaſting life.</p>
            <p>That ſo her Brother had done before her, and would never repent, nor confeſs, till he was upon the Gallows ready to be turned over, and then out all came, when he could live no longer to the Devil, then he would go to God; and God muſt be put off with the Devils leavings.</p>
            <p>To which ſhe rejoyned, that her Brother had made a Godly end, and ſhe was ſure he was now in Heaven, and did wiſh ſhe might make as good an End. <hi>And ſaid I, I pray God you may make a better!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that the Curioſity of my Reader, who will inquire concerning her Brother, may be ſatisfied: I ſhall give an account of him briefly, craving pardon for amuſeing him with this Digreſſion. Take then his and ſubſcribed with his own hand at <hi>Lanceſton</hi> in <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall, April</hi> the Third, 1675. Juſt as he was a turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over, for till then he would make none.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="confession">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:96502:26"/>
            <head>The Confeſſion of <hi>John Codmore</hi> Condemned to be Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and Made by him at the Gallows.</head>
            <p n="1">1. HE began to commit the ſin of Theft firſt upon Peaſe and Apples.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The next thing he ſtole, was Figs from a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Stall, unknown to the Owner.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Next he wronged his Father in giving away his Syder unknown to him, and by reaſon of perſwaſions of others. <hi>And he Married againſt his Fathers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. When he was with his Maſter <hi>John Temple</hi> of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merton</hi> Pariſh, he took Money for Dying of Cloth and Stockings unknown to his ſaid Maſter.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Next, when he was with <hi>Robert Strong</hi> of <hi>Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> he there received Money for Dying of Cloth, Stockings, and Wool, unknown to his Maſter, which did belong unto his Maſter, and in his Service went into a Garden, and ſtole Goesberries and Cherries.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Next he ſtole from <hi>Peter Slade</hi> of <hi>Tregony,</hi> Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Pounds of Wool, and alſo kept from him Dy-ſtuff which did belong unto him.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Next he ſtole from <hi>Samuel Pentire</hi> of <hi>Tregony,</hi> One piece of Sarge, who brought it to him to Dye, and never had the return of it more.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Next he ſtole from <hi>John Cooling</hi> of <hi>Verrian,</hi> a Yard and half of Sarge, and ſeveral Pounds of Wool.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Next he ſtole from <hi>John Bullock</hi> of the ſame Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, One piece of Sarge, who brought it to him to Die, and never had it more.</p>
            <p n="10">10. He ſtole from another perſon whoſe name he hath forgot, Two Yards and half of Sarge, which were bought to be Dyed, and ſeverall pare of Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings from ſeveral people, which they never had again.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:96502:27"/>
            <p n="11">11. He ſtole from <hi>Henry Jellings</hi> of <hi>Tregony,</hi> One piece of Sarge, who brought it to him to Dye, and never had the return of it more.</p>
            <p n="12">12. He ſtole from <hi>Robert Strong</hi> of <hi>Plymouth,</hi> Three Yards of Sarge, Two Yards of Cloth, and Four pair of Stockings, at another time Four Sticks of Brazil.</p>
            <p n="13">13. He ſtole from <hi>William Weeks</hi> of <hi>Plymouth,</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Yards of Sarge.</p>
            <p n="14">14. He ſtole from a Widow woman of <hi>Loo,</hi> out of a Box that was in a Chamber wherein he lay, Eight Shillings and Six pence.</p>
            <p n="15">15. He ſtole from his Uncle <hi>John Codmore,</hi> a Dun Nag.</p>
            <p n="16">16. He ſtole out of <hi>John Temples</hi> Houſe of <hi>Tamer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Eight Yards of Linnen, and One pair of Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and at another time ſtole from him Fourteen Yards of Sarge, Three Yards of Cloth, and Eleven pair of Stockings.</p>
            <p n="17">17. He ſtole from his Father, Money out of his Pockets at ſeveral times, and once Eighteen Shillings.</p>
            <p n="18">18. He ſtole from <hi>Tryphena Channings</hi> of St. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phens,</hi> One Silver Thimble, and Two Yards and half of Sarge, and a mans Sarge Coat, for which he broke a Window.</p>
            <p n="19">19. He ſtole from <hi>John Walter</hi> of the ſaid Pariſh, a white Mare, Bridle, Saddle, and Gambadoes.</p>
            <p n="20">20. He broke an Houſe in <hi>Pillington,</hi> and ſtole from thence Five Silver Spoons, One Silver Trimble, and a Silver Whiſtle.</p>
            <p n="21">21. He ſtole from <hi>Hugh Northam</hi> of <hi>Tamerton,</hi> the Summ of Nine and thirty Pounds, Fifteen Shillings, and Ten Pence in Money, and One Scarf, Six Dozen and Four Silver Buttons, Twenty Gold Buttons, a ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Knot of Scarlet Ribband, and Four ſmall Knots of the ſame, and ſome Silver Bobbin.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:96502:27"/>
            <p n="22">22. He confeſt he ſold his Wife to a Millar, for Five pound on a Bill, half to be paid on <hi>Eaſter</hi> Munday, and the other half to be paid the <hi>Whitſun</hi> Munday after.</p>
            <p n="23">23. He ſtole from <hi>Hatherly Moore</hi> Two Steers, and fold them at <hi>Plymouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">24. He brake the Houſe of <hi>John Trapling</hi> of <hi>Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lington,</hi> and from thence ſtole meat dreſt.</p>
            <p n="25">25. He went into <hi>Thomas Mallets</hi> Houſe of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> at the top of the Chimney, and his Wife heard it, ſo he went out, and ſtole nothing.</p>
            <p n="26">26. He was alſo tempted to break the Houſe of <hi>Tryphena Channings,</hi> if ſhe had not changed her lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Room, from the Chamber to the under Room, he had then intended to have ſtolen away her Box wherein her money lay.</p>
            <p n="27">27. He ſtole a Gooſe at <hi>Lee</hi> in <hi>Pillington</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</p>
            <p n="28">28. He was alſo riding in St. <hi>Blazy,</hi> and ſaw Geeſe in the way, he ſtruck one and killed it, and carried it away with him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I certifie my offence, that all the world may know the effects of ſin, and hereto I have ſet my hand, the day above written. And the Lord give me Repentance whilſt it is time.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Codmore.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="narrative">
            <p>REader this is a fair Catalogue! A goodly Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roll! And a very ſweet Penitent! And that I do not wrong his memory, give me leave to tell thee, that of all this money which he laſt ſtole from Mr. <hi>Northam</hi> (and it is credibly reported the Sum was double to what he confeſſed,) he never took
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:96502:28"/>any care to reſtore one Farthing; nay, ordered a conſiderable Summ of it, I think Thirty Pound, to be put out for his Child; and gave order unto his wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Brother in Law to go to <hi>Loo,</hi> and in that Chamber where he lay laſt, hanging to the Vallance of his Bed next to the Wall, he ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld find a Purſe of Money, which accordingly he fetcht, but what is become of it is unknown.</p>
            <p>However at the Execution of his wicked Siſter, we may chance to hear ſome farther tale and tidings thereof. But for this fellow, he hath a Twelve month ſince received his Doom, and is gone unto his place, and there we leave him.</p>
            <p>And now let us return Reader from our Digreſſion, though I think we have not been much, nor long out of our way.</p>
            <p>Finding no good ſucceſs in my labors with the Nurſe, I ſent for the Maid to come unto me. Who being ſhut into the Chamber with me, I aſked her what ſhe did think would become of her pretious Soul; that it was better worth than a World, and it was a Thouſand pitties that a Jewel of ſuch ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable worth and value ſhould be loſt for ever. That now it was in a very dangerous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtate, and ready to periſh irrecoverably. That as ſhe had by her envy, malice, Inſtigation, and Correſpondence with the Devil Murdered her two Miſtreſſes, ſo ſhe alſo had Murdered her own Soul and Body: And that as they were dead and Buried, ſo would ſhe alſo ſhortly die a very horrible death, and without won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful mercy be ſwallowed up of everlaſting wrath. That the Fire which was to conſume her in <hi>Plymouth</hi> would be very painful, but the Fire of Hell in which ſhe muſt live and lye for ever would be inſupportable. That her many and mighty ſins had brought her to this woful condition. And I added, <hi>How will you get out of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:96502:28"/>
            <p>Poor wretch! She fell a trembling and weeping, and deſired my help and direction, and ſhe would la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor to follow it.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, my Bowels yearning on her, and mingling my tears with hers, I told her I was heartily glad to hear ſuch words drop from her mouth, and through Gods bleſſing ſhe would never want it.</p>
            <p>Then I told her. <hi>Anne,</hi> do you ſit down in ſome ſecret place, and review your life, and look over all your ways, and call your ſelf to an account for all the ſins that you can remember your ſelf Guilty of; and conſider chiefly that your heart and nature are deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately wicked, that there dwelleth in you nothing that is good, and that you cannot do any thing that is good, no not ſo much of your ſelf as think a good thought, much leſs to Convert and turn your ſelf to God. Then remember every one of the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and how that you have tranſgreſt againſt them, eſpecially againſt the Sixth. <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill;</hi> and that for every one of theſe ſins of yours, even for the leaſt you have deſerved to burn in Hell: Oh! Then how many Hells have you merited.</p>
            <p>Beſides, conſider all the mercies of God beſtowed upon you, as your <hi>Life, Health, Liberty, Friends, Food;</hi> and to live in a Land where the Goſpel is preached, and the way to Heaven revealed and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, and yet how unworthily have you abuſed them to the diſhonor of the Lord that gave them. But principally conſider that all your ſins have been committed againſt God the Father, that Created you, that gave you life and being, againſt God the Son Chriſt Jeſus, who became man, and died for you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anne,</hi> ſaid I, this makes your ſin exceeding ſinful, a very horrible ſin, that Chriſt Jeſus to ſave you from ſin and Hell, died for you, was crucified and accurſed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:96502:29"/>for you, loſt his heart blood for you, and underwent the torments of Hell for you, to keep and ſave you from them: And yet by every ſin that you have been Guilty of, you have Crucified Chriſt afreſh, you have ſtabbed him to the heart, drawn freſh blood from him. For not one of your ſins can be pardoned without his blood, and you have been very prodigal of it, to ſpill, and deſpiſe, and trample it under Foot, which is Helliſh ingratitude.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Will you ſet home this meditation upon your Heart?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, conſider, that you have ſinned againſt the Holy Spirit of God, who ſanctified you in Baptiſm unto his Service; and that quite contrary to the end and intent of God in Baptizing you, that you might repent, and renounce ſin, you have wallowed in it all your daies, and grieved the good Spirit of God, and only gratified and ſerved the Devil.</p>
            <p>And having done this, do you throw your ſelf not upon your knees, but flat upon your face, upon the earth before God, and think as if you were at the very mouth of Hell, and ready to be caſt headlong into the torments of it; that are endleſs, eaſeleſs, and remedileſs; and then with ſhowrs of tears, and with as much <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Grief</hi> as you can poſſibly confeſs all theſe ſins unto God, and beg of God to give you Repentance unto life, to <hi>Weep, Mourn,</hi> and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded for them; and never ſeave <hi>Praying, Sighing,</hi> and <hi>Groaning</hi> unto God in Prayer, till he do make your hard heart wax ſoft within you, and that you be chiefly abaſed and humbled, that you have ſinned againſt God, who is your beſt Friend, Saviour, and alone Comforter.</p>
            <p>Beſides, do this at night upon your Bed, and be up early at this work, and deſire the Lord that your late Repentance, may be a true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:96502:29"/>
            <p>Having promiſed me, that ſhe would take this courſe, we came out unto the other Priſoners. And ſpeaking unto the Man condemned for coyning, I told him, and his Companion who ſtole a Mare, (but is ſince mercifully reprieved,) That God had ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not Steal,</hi> and as he that Murdered by Gods Law deſerved everlaſting death in Hell, ſo by that ſame Law, did he that ſtole; that burning in Hell was a worſe puniſhment than hanging upon a Gallows.</p>
            <p>That it was a wickedneſs againſt the light of nature that they were guilty of: That the very Heathen who knew not God, puniſhed it with as much ſeverity as our Laws.</p>
            <p>That they would not willingly have others ſo uſe them, to take away their goods from them:</p>
            <p>That every Man had a Right, Title and Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to the fruit of his own and honeſt Labors.</p>
            <p>That it was a ſin againſt the whole Land, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to invade the Prerogatives of the King, ſuch as coyning was, being inſeparable from the Crown, and a moſt glorious Flower of it.</p>
            <p>That he who would ſtrike at the Royalties of the King, would never ſtick nor boggle to make away the Life of the King, which was ſuch a piece of damnable impiety in it ſelf and conſequences, that none but an incarnate Devil would be guilty of.</p>
            <p>That they ſhould do well to ſeek the pace of God in time, and to wreſtle mightily with him for Grace, Repentance, and Forgiveneſs, that ſo they might not periſh everlaſtingly. Their time was ſhort, their work great, it was no eaſie matter to get to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>That I had known many very holy, mortified, and godly Perſons that had ſpent Threeſcore years in a Religious Life, and cloſe walking with God, yet to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:96502:30"/>be full of fears and doubts they ſhould never get to Heaven. And that they had much more cauſe to work out their Salvation with fear and trembling.</p>
            <p>And in the upſhot told them, that if they would ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly and heartily embrace and follow theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, if they would to day, whilſt it is called to day, hearken to the Voice of God, and nor harden their Hearts, there was hope for them in their latter end, For their was forgiveneſs with God that he might he feared, yea with the Lord there was mercy, and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Redemption. Other Miniſters coming in, I bad them farewel for the preſent.</p>
            <p>THe next morning about Eight of the Clock, I viſited them again, and ſound with them Mr. <hi>G. T.</hi> a worthy Miniſter of <hi>Exon,</hi> who gave me an account of the unſuccesfulneſs of his Labors, as to that wicked Woman the Nurſe; and then in a very pathetical and devout prayer, moſt pertinent to their conditions, with great meltings of his own heart and affections, commended them unto the Lord.</p>
            <p>When he was gone, I dealt again with the Nurſe, but no more privately as heretofore; I urged her to repent of her horrid Murders, to acknowledg them, and take the ſhame of them to her ſelf: That ſhe muſt do it. God and Man, Heaven and Earth required it from her mouth.</p>
            <p>She ſtill asks me, <hi>Sir, what will you have me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs an untruth unto you, a matter of which I am not Guilty?</hi> I told her that none believed her, that it was a moſt improbable thing that thoſe Perſons who wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed againſt her, ſome of them being to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg Perſons fearing God, hating a lie, ſhould ever accuſe her falſly. They had no temptations to it, ſhe never having wronged nor offended them, that as far as I knew, the were as much her Friends, as her
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:96502:30"/>Miſtreſſes, that there was neither profit, nor advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, nor pleaſure, nor honor accrewing to them in taking away her life, and they were too tender, and made more Conſcience than ſo, to draw upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the guilt of innocent Blood.</p>
            <p>And finally, I told her, that ſhe had<note n="*" place="margin">made</note> ſwopt a Bargain with the Devil for ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to her own deſtruction, that all would out at laſt, as cunningly and cloſely as ſhe did carry it, before Men and Angels; and ſaid I, you are one of the moſt bloody Women, that ever came into this Goal, you are guilty of Two Murthers upon your Miſtreſſes, guilty of a Third before God, having drawn in this poor Girl like a Devil, as you are, to joyn with you to ruin them and her ſelf alſo, and though ſhe ſuffered juſtly from Man, yet her Blood would be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired from your hands by God, and then you muſt anſwer for the ſhortning of her days, and that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction ſhe and you have brought upon her ſelf; ſo that ſhe was drowned over and over in Blood-guiltineſs: And I did as verily believe ſhe would be in Hell, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs there were a very wonderful change wrought upon her, as that old Murderer her Father the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil was.</p>
            <p>Theſe words extorted tears from her, but no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and ſhe prayed me to have better thoughts and hopes of her. I told her, I wiſh I had ſome grounds for them, but I could have none, till I ſaw her ſtony Heart rent and ſhivered to pieces, and her Bones broken under the ſence of her Helliſh wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſhe did not continue to reject the Counſels of God to her own deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Upon this her Accuſers, that unthought of, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to me, were at the Door, being admitted, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred with her; and I betook my ſelf to the poor Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, the Maid.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:96502:31"/>
            <p>This is a ſad, too ſad a Truth. After condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion crowds of vulgar Perſons throng in upon theſe Malefactors: The covetous Keepers for love of a piece of money letting them in, who by their looſe; idle, and impertinent diſcourſes, obſtruct the ſucceſs of Miniſterial Labors. However this poor Maid aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me, that her thoughts had been upon my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels in the night, and ſhe wou'd make it her buſineſs to do it more effectually, and withal, added that ſhe ſaw her ſelf undone for ever.</p>
            <p>To which I replied, No, ſhe was nearer Heaven than ſhe was aware of. That her ſins were not too great for God to pardon. That ſhe ſhould remember Three Texts of Scripture that I would tell her.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>This is a true and faithful ſaying, worthy of her acceptation, that Jeſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners, of whom I am chief.</hi> Yea Sir, (ſaith ſhe,) I am the greateſt ſinner in <hi>Plymouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That whoſoever comes unto Chriſt,</hi> that is, <hi>believes in Chriſt, he would in no wiſe caſt out.</hi> That for her to believe in and come to Chriſt, was no other than this; That ſeeing her ſelf by reaſon of ſin to be a damned Wretch, ſhe caſt her ſelf upon the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercies of God becauſe of Chriſts death, with hope and expectation of them, and waiting for them.</p>
            <p>And then Thirdly, <hi>That the Blood of Chriſt clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from all ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſhe ſhould meditate and think upon theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious words of God, and reſolve that ſhe would live and die with them in her Heart. And if ſhe did, and grieved unfeignedly for her ſins, loathed them, and her ſelf for them, my Soul for hers, ſhe ſhould never periſh. For Jeſus Chriſt was a moſt abſolute and compleat Saviour, able and willing to ſave the worſt of Mankind, that would be ſaved by him upon theſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:96502:31"/>his Terms, and therefore would ſave her. Upon this ſhe wept again.</p>
            <p>Having comforted her, and done ſomewhat to bind up her wounds; I added, <hi>Anne,</hi> there are yet ſome other works for you; you muſt die in Charity with the world, and crave pardon as from God, ſo from Man, eſpecially from your Maſter whom you have ſo grievouſly wronged. You muſt alſo in particular for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give this bloody Woman the Nurſe, that hath ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced you to this great ſin, and to your perdition. Will you? Can you do it? If you do it not from your heart, God will never forgive you. <hi>Sir,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>I wit, I do it. And it ſhould not grieve me if ſhe lived, though l died only for this Fact. I forgive her, a I expect forgiveneſs from God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then I added, She muſt beware of miſpending her time, or looſing a moment of it; ſhe ſhould take heed of vain thoughts, ſhe muſt be much in private Prayer, and not be long, but ſhort, ſhort in Prayer, but often. She muſt hearken to all the good counſels of Gods Miniſters that would come and viſit her, and do them to the utmoſt. She ſhould be as Spiritual, Holy, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, Humble, Serious, and Heavenly minded as poſſible. She ſhould not take any great care of her Body, the leſs the better, as to eating, drinking, or ſleep: Her whole thoughts and care ſhould be ſpent about her Soul, and its ſalvation.</p>
            <p>And to conclude, <hi>Anne,</hi> ſaid I, it is a hard work to die at any time, but for one in thy condition very hard indeed. But however, once thy peace is made with God, and thou haſt repented of thy ſin, and thrown thy poor Soul upon Sovereign mercy in the Blood of Jeſus, never fear death. Take it humbly, patiently, and ſubmiſſively. Bear the indignation of the Lord becauſe thou haſt ſinned, accept of the puniſhment of thine iniquity, yea be thankful unto God, that thou
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:96502:32"/>mayeſt be Burnt here and not hereafter. I hope the Lord will make thy death eaſie, ſhort, and comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Thou art yet a ſtranger to the joys of Gods Salvation, and to the comforts of his Holy Spirit: But it may be the Lord will give them to thee in thy bitter torments, and then thou wilt ſcarce feel them; or if he ſhall detain them from thee, yet his Grace is ſufficient for thee; believe in the Lord Jeſus, and thou ſhalt be ſaved.</p>
            <p>And finiſhing my diſcourſe with her, ſhe asked whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe ſhould not ſee me again, eſpecially when ſhe was to ſuffer, for ſhe earneſtly requeſted my help, my aſſiſtance to her in that hour.</p>
            <p>I promiſed, if it could be obtained, ſhe ſhould have it.</p>
            <p>Being now returned to the reſt of the Malefactors, I ſpake ſomething of the Glories of that other World, where truly Penitent and believing ſinners were a go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, what an unſpeakable happineſs God had prepared for them, and what wonderful rich grace this was on Gods part, that he ſhould promiſe and tender it unto them. Two of whom I hope were broken hearted, though they wanted much knowledge, and much of that Compunction that they ought to have; that if they would endeavor after more Grace, God, who was the God of all Grace, would give liberally unto them, and never upbraid them with their paſt ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</p>
            <p>That the promiſes were not made ſo much unto the meaſure and degree of Grace, as to the nature and Truth of Grace: That a Grain of Gold was as truly Gold, as an heap or Mountain; That the Lord was no reſpecter of Perſons, but an Univerſal, a Common Saviour: That he deſpiſed not the day of ſmall things, <hi>He would not quench the ſmoaking Flax, nor break the bruiſed Reed,</hi> nor caſt off any ſelf-confounded, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:96502:32"/>ſelf-condemned wrerches. That whatever their ſins had been, they ſhould beware of doubting or deſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gods mercies. Their deſpair of Salvation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a greater ſin than Murder or High Treaſon. That I was not ignorant of Satans devices, no ſtranger to his Wiles and Stratagems, who when he could keep them no longer in Chains of darkneſs and Impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, would put Souls upon Over-doing in Repentance, and over whelm them with horrors.</p>
            <p>They ſhould look to this and believe it, live and die upon it, that Chriſt Jeſus was more willing to ſave them, than they were to be ſaved by him, that though they were to die ſhameful and painful deaths, you to be Hanged; and you to be Burnt. Yet here was a comfortable meditation, it was as eaſie going to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from the Stake and Gallows, as from their Beds; and when their Souls were departing out of their Bodies, Gods Holy Angels would convey them into Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>At this good news my Two Penitents wept; and I hope Tears of Joy.</p>
            <p>And turning my ſelf unto the Nurſe, Woman, ſaid I, it is the very grief of my Soul, and makes my heart bleed within me, that not one Syllable or tittle of theſe good words of Gods gracious promiſes belongs to thee. <hi>This is the Children Bread, it muſt not be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto Dogs and Devils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having finiſhed my diſcourſe, I gathered up the particulars, and ſpread them before the Lord in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, begging grace and glory for them: And that his Divine Majeſty would yet mollifie that Adamant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and take away the heart of ſtone, and give an heart of fleſh, and open the Brazen Doors that this Captive of Hell might go forth, and give glory to him by a full and ingenious Confeſſion, and find mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ere ſhe went hence, and ſhould be ſeen no more.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:96502:33"/>
            <p>Taking my leave of them, hoping another day to ſee them in Heaven, I departed the Chamber. As I was going out the Nurſe pulls me by the Coat, deſiring private conference with me.</p>
            <p>This very much ſurprized me, conceiving that ſhe began to relent, and that Satan was a fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>But I was miſerably miſtaken, when with Tears in her eyes ſhe intreated me to deal effectually with the Maid, to declare who ſet her upon it to accuſe her, that ſhe might know them that contrived her death.</p>
            <p>I told her, I had already; and in Three conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces could never find her to vary one tittle. That I ſaw the Maid ingenious and Penitent, but had not the leaſt token of true Repentance from her; That ſhe was a Brazen Impudent Hypocrite, thus to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble with God and Man, to pretend Innocency, when her own Conſcience convinces her of the Guilt of ſo much blood. That ſhe ſhould not deceive her ſelf, God would not be mocked, as ſhe had Sown ſo ſhe ſhould Reap. She kept the Devils Counſel, and to the Devil ſhe would go. I had ſpent my time and Spirits for the good of her Soul, but I ſaw no good iſſue thereof; and therefore look to it Woman, Look to it, that this do not make thy Hell hotter than Ordinary.</p>
            <p>And then added one word, Prethee tell me, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou haſt no ſin at all upon thy Spirit, that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles thee?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No, Sir, none it all I thank God. I never wronged any one in my life. I never hurt my Miſtris, nor took a Needle of Threed from her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I asked her father. Whether ſhe had not the Gold which her Brother ſtole from Maſter <hi>Northam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>She ſaid No.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:96502:33"/>
            <p>I told her my Intelligence came from her own Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who avowed that her Brother gave it her in a Paper to take to his Child, and that ſhe took it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to the Child, but then immediately took it from him again.</p>
            <p>All which ſhe ſtiffly denies, maintaining ſhe never ſaw nor knew of One Farthing of that Money, either Gold or Silver: That her Brother was too wiſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt it to her a poor Woman for his Child, who had a Child of her own. But this is downright Lying and aequivocation, as you will hear at the day of her Execution.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="narrative">
            <head>Coming down in the Court of the Jail, the Priſoners flock about me, to whom I addreſſed my ſelf in ſhort.</head>
            <p>SOme Thirteen years ago in my firſt Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I was confined unto this place, but bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed be God for no evil that I had done, unleſs to work in my place and calling be an evil. However, I learnt, from that day to this, to compaſſionate all Priſoners. And the mercies (being a ſtranger and Priſoner, I found by the good Providence of my God, in this Houſe,) have made me pay yearly ſome Vows and Thank-offerings to him within theſe Walls. That I would leave ſomething with them, which ſhould be better than Money, if they would aceept it.</p>
            <p>Some of you are now Reprieved, others Burnt in the Hand and to be diſcharged: Take heed, Sin no more, leſt a worſe thing befall you. If you do not go out of a Priſon new Men, and new Creatures, your old ſins will return again upon you, and the Devil that brought you hither, will enter once more into
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:96502:34"/>you with Seven worſe Devils, and your latter end will be worſe than your beginning. If you do not mend your Lives, avoid and abhor your former ſins, obey, ſerve, and fear God, labor diligently in your callings, keep your Church, and wait upon Gods Holy Ordinances: If you do not leave all your wicked Company, and wicked Courſes, 'ile aſſure you, God will never bleſs you, you do but get looſe from a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in Earth, to be clapt up at laſt everlaſting Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners with the Devil in his Gaol of Hell.</p>
            <p>Whilſt my affairs called me Home-wards, it pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God to ſtir up the Hearts of many Miniſters in the City of <hi>Exon</hi> to viſit theſe Priſoners, and to Proſecute that good work which was begun in them.</p>
            <p>I am ſorry that no Memorials of their Pious Labors, and Divine Diſcourſes are fallen into my Hands, that might have enricht the Soul of my Reader, and been an embelliſhment to this courſe Paper.</p>
            <p>Something occurred in Two Letters, which (crav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pardon of my worthy Friends for inſerting it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their Privity,) I here offer to the World.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>I Have yours of the Nine and twentieth inſtant, and immediately made it my work to inquire after the Miniſters which viſited the Poor Priſoners Condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Poyſoning Miſtris <hi>Weeks,</hi> &amp;c. And after my beſt Inquiry, can only learn in the General, that ſeveral have been with them, and that the Girl ſeems more Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent than the Nurſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who ſtifly denies the Fact. I do not hear that either the one or the other have been abſolved or received the Sacrament. Maſter Treaſurer-Hall was Ordinary, but I have not ſpoken with him. My affairs and buſineſs (which called me out of Town) would not permit me to ſee them till this day. I tarried an hour
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:96502:34"/>and half at leaſt with them, and upon my entring into the Room, where the poor wretches were kept, I found the young Girl with a Bible, and another Priſoner with a Book, (I preſume reading to them, for he told me he did uſe to do ſo.) Directing my ſelf to them both, I did the beſt I could to repreſent their ſad condition, and the demerits of their ſins, eſpecially of that horrid one, for which they were Condemned.</p>
                  <p>The Girl ſeemed ſomewhat ſenſible; but I ſaw no relenting in the Nurſe, which made me afterward direct my diſcourſe chiefly unto her. But after all I could ſay, I perceived it had little effect upon her; which made me tell her at my departure, that I was ſorry, I had not the leaſt word of Comfort for her. But however, I told her, I did hope my diſcourſe would prevail with her for a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, if ſo, I ſhould be very glad of it, and upon any other notice from her, would readily come to her, though it were at midnight.</p>
                  <p>She ſeemed moſt ſenſible of theſe laſt words, and as I think, told me (for ſhe ſpake low) that ſhe would Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of it.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Exon <date>March <hi>27. 1676.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>I am Sir, Your Brother and Servant.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:96502:35"/>
            <p>From another I had this.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>ALL the times I was with them, I could diſcern no great alteration in any one of them, the Nurſe ſtill refuſing to confeſs any thing, and the Girl indeed utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome good expreſſions, but I could not diſcern that they proceeded from any great ſence within, or were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with any affection. I hope God may have ſucceeded your endeavors there with them, better than he hath ours here. Mr. D. was with them thrice ſince I was, but could do no great good upon them, nor diſcern any thing in them: Yet I have heard the Nurſe ſhould deſire to ſpeak with him again, but to what purpoſe I know not. Tis reported ſhe ſhould ſay, <hi>She knew ſhe ſhould be Damned, but not for this Crime.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Exon <date>March <hi>30, 1676.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Sir, Yours to love and ſerve you in our Lord Jeſus,</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:96502:35"/>
            <p>What ever the effect and Fruit of their labors was, ſhe gave them this enſuing Confeſſion, which one of thoſe Reverend Miniſters, that panted after her Souls Salvation, took from her mouth, and hath Cloathed it in theſe words.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="confession">
            <head>The Ingenious and true Confeſſion of <hi>Anne Evans,</hi> concerning the horrid and cruel Murder of <hi>Elizabeth Weeks,</hi> and <hi>Mary Pengelley.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ENvy being once at the height, it put in Execution with a Witneſs. This Nurſe having by ſome means cauſed her Husband to receive words from her Miſtris, he was pleaſed to be very angry with his Wiſe for the ſame, and withal threatens her to leave her. And departed for a Fortnights time; whereupon began an hatching of this Barbarous action by the ſaid Nurſe, ſaying ſhe would fit her for it; for ſhe her Miſtris was the cauſe of her Husbands going from her, (as ſhe ſaid) and endeavored to put it in practiſe with perſwading the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> to go to Maſter <hi>Mathews</hi> the Apothecary for <hi>Ratsbane,</hi> telling her ſhe ſhould ask it for the poyſoning of Rats and Mice, ſaying, it will do her work in as ſhort a time as one might go to the Gate and back again, and then they ſhould live as merry as the days were long, when the old Devil was gone. Saying, ſhe knew one who was poyſoned in as little time with it and ſome Cream.</p>
            <p>Whereupon like a true and Faithful Servant, the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> refuſeth and rejects the ſaid ſayings, and would by no means do it.</p>
            <p>Here we muſt ſtop a while, and give you to underſtand how much this poor Creature lived in fear of the Nurſe, and by that means neglected the diſcovery of it to the deſtroying of her Body, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the deſtroying
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:96502:36"/>of her Soul. For there is mercy with the Lord, that he may be Feared.</p>
            <p>Now the Devil having once got hold on her Heart, neglects no opportunities, but puts her on it with great ſubtilties and invention: The Nurſe laying, as it is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by all circumſtances, a clean Paper twiſted at both ends with Poyſon in it in the path of the Garden; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that this <hi>Anne Evans</hi> was to go forth to gather Herbs to put into the Pot, (according to her Miſtreſſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,) ſhe finds the Paper lying in her way, which ſhe took up, and brought in, and ſhews it to this Nurſe again, asking her what it was, who pretended ſhe knew not, and with all bidding her put it out of her hand, the Nurſe eyed her where ſhe lay'd it, which was in the Kitchin on a ſhelf.</p>
            <p>Going afterward to the Conduit for Water, at her return it came into her mind, to look on that thing once more, which ſhe had taken up in the Garden, and it was gone off from the ſhelf; which no body elſe could take but the ſaid Nurſe, for it was at Eight of the Clock at night, and no body there but ſhe.</p>
            <p>Then the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> ſaw her grinding it on the Harth with Two Tiles, and demanding her what ſhe was doing, ſhe cryed Peace! we ſhall have brave sport, if you will but put this into the old Womans Diſh. She through her enticements and ſtrong perſwaſions, not knowing what it was, or that the end of it would be death, being not willing to have her displeaſure. For ſhe lived in great fear of offending the Nurſe, becauſe ſhe was in great favor with the young Miſtreſs, thinking that if ſhe did not conſent to her requeſt ſhe ſhould fare the worſe for it.</p>
            <p>And further the ſaid <hi>Anne Evans</hi> doth teſtifie that the ſame Sunday ſhe was ſent for ſome drink, which ſhe brought to the Nurſe, and the Nurſe did Warm it, and put a bit of Bread into it, and drank up a good draught
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:96502:36"/>of it, and filled it up again afterward with other drink, in which ſhe had ſteeped ſome of that Powder all night, and gave it to the old Miſtriſs to drink.</p>
            <p>Here is a Conſeſſion Harmonical with that ſhe made for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, ſhe varied nothing from firſt to laſt in it. So that as the Serpent drew in <hi>Eve,</hi> in like manner did this wicked Nurſe beguile this poor Maid into the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="narrative">
            <p>ON Wedneſday the 29. of <hi>March,</hi> they left <hi>Exon,</hi> and were brought on Horſeback to <hi>Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> in order to their execution.</p>
            <p>At the Bridg end, as they were coming out of the City, that vile Woman was heard to lay unto the Hangman boaſtingly, <hi>That ſhe had known many Men in her life,</hi> and uſed ſeveral other obſcene expreſſions, that I will not ſoil my Paper, nor make my Reader bluſh at the Relation of them.</p>
            <p>In their journey, the Girl was very penſive, cared for little or no refreſhment, and at the laſt place where they baited, being deſired to take ſome ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; ſhe replied, <hi>There was other work for her than to eat or drink, ſhe had a Soul to ſave, would look wholly after that, and no more care for her Body; which ſhould neither eat, nor drink more in this world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Nurſe was of a far different temper and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment, far from ſeriouſneſs, or thoughts of Death and Eternity; The Executioner was her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and if he had not defiled her, they are both abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minably wronged.</p>
            <p>Now they return again to <hi>Plymouth.</hi> At their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance they are attended by Thouſands of People. Perſons of all Age and Quality ran to meet them.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:96502:37"/>They are gazed at as ſo many Monſters. Every one paſſeth his cenſure on them; ſome with bowels of pitty on the poor Girl, ſcarce any one hath Charity for the Nurſe. They went from this Town with their ſin, and under guilt: They return unto it with ſhame, and ſorrow, and under wrath.</p>
            <p>Being conducted unto their Chamber, the Reverend and Learned Miniſters of <hi>Plymouth,</hi> Dr. <hi>Aſhton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Collings,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Read</hi> viſits them, and diſcourſe with them, but the Throng of Spectators was ſo great, that for the preſent much good could not be done by them. Yet ſo ſtrong a flame of divine love toward the Souls of theſe condemned wretches was kindled in the hearts of thoſe grave Divines, that they return again unto them after Ten, and though late at night, yet ſpent a conſiderable ſpace of time in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious conferences with them, and muſter up all their arguments to induce that obſtinate ſinner the Nurſe to confeſs, and forſake the Devil, and to accept of Gods tender mercies. But the flinty Rock will ſooner guſh out with Waters, and the Adamant be broken to pieces by the Hammer, than her unmoveable Soul utter forth one Syllable of guilt. Heart-work, is hard work. None but the Divine and Omnipotent Arm can unlock it's Doors, or break its Bars in pieces.</p>
            <p>With the Maid they had no difficulty, ſhe owneth, and confeſſeth all. Her deſires are for mercy at the hands of God, acknowledging ſhe deſerved and expected none from Men.</p>
            <p>They conclude their charitable Viſit with ſeeking God, the Reverend Doctor praying moſt fervently for them.</p>
            <p>I alſo viſited them again, and renued my aſſaults and batteries againſt this ſtrong hold of the Devil; but ſhe reſiſts, ſtands out againſt God, and all his
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:96502:37"/>Counſels; ſhe reſolves from firſt to laſt, whatever parleys ſhe hath with Heaven, let the Lord humble himſelf never ſo much unto ſo baſe a Murderer, ſhe may treat with him, but unleſs ſhe can obtain her own Terms, her own Articles and Conditions, ſhe will not ſurrender. Sill ſhe hideth her ſin, as <hi>Adam;</hi> ſtill concealeth ſhe the ſecret of Hell, as if ſhe had been ſworn Privy Counſeller unto the Devil. She will ſooner bite out her Tongue, and ſpit it out of her Mouth, or ſeal up the door of her Lips, than let the <hi>depoſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um</hi> Satan have vent, and ſee the Sun. So that I could ſigh unto my ſelf as that <hi>German Philip, The old Satan is too hard for young Melancthon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was high time to leave her, upon whom no good impreſſions could be wrought.</p>
            <p>I then betook my ſelf to the poor Penitent, and ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her how ſhe did, How it went with her Soul? She anſwers me, <hi>Never was a poor Creature ſo cheated out of her life: But I forgive the Nurſe front my Heart. And Sir, Though my ſins are many, yet Gods mercies are more, and if Chriſt bath not merits enough to ſave me, I will be contented to be damned eternally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And afterward inquiring of her into the grounds and reaſons of this her confidence, ſhe told me, <hi>she ſaw her ſin, ſhe was unfeignedly ſorry for it, and not only that it was committed againſt her Miſtreſſes, and had rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them, and her ſelf here; but chiefly this grieved her, that ſhe had thereby diſhonored God her Heavenly Father, who had made her, and Jeſus Chriſt who had died for her, and God the Holy Ghoſt, who had ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied her to become his Servant. That however, ſhe would not deſpare of mercy. For the Thief upon the Croſs found mercy from our Saviour at the laſt hour, and I Queſtion not, that he my Saviour hath mercy for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reader, I give thee her very words, neither adding to them, nor ſubſtracting from them; and if they do
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:96502:38"/>do not melt thee in reading, I muſt aſſure thee they did me in heating them.</p>
            <p>Her Siſters being come to her weeping and crying, ſhe was deſired to ſpeak to them, and urged becauſe her time was ſhort, ſhe anſwered, <hi>My time is ſhort in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and I am drawing near unto Eternity, but I hope in God to an Eternity of Happineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My great work now was to ſettle her Spirit, and to corroborate her Soul againſt the horrors of her death; and told her after many other diſcourſes, <hi>Anne,</hi> thou art happier than many here, for I hope be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Twenty four hours be paſt, thou wilt be in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Hold faſt thy hope and confidence in Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which ſhal have a good recompence of Reward. No matter for thy puniſhment, ſince thou haſt a pardon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea Sir,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>I believe, and receive this true and faithful ſaying, worthy of all acceptation, that Jeſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners, of whom I am chief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having got a little ſilence, (and very little indeed it was, the noiſe and tumult of the people ever and anon drowning my voice,) I prayed with theſe Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, and wiſhed them a good Night.</p>
            <p>But ſleep they did not. Every hour increaſeth their fears.</p>
            <p>The day of their Execution is now come, and early in the morning I gave them another viſit, comforted and confirmed the poor Maid, who deſired me not to leave her at her ſufferings, and dealt again with the Nurſe, though to as little purpoſe as formerly, and then ſought God by Prayer in their behalf.</p>
            <p>That duty finiſhed, Turning my diſcourſe to the Maid, <hi>Anne,</hi> ſaid I, Thy time flies away, thy end is very near, take off thy heart wholly from the world. Be dead unto thy Relations, tell them, the beſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and kindneſs they can do thee is not to ſee thee, but pray for thee, and let all thy thoughts and deſires
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:96502:38"/>be unto God, to be at home with him: long now to be in Heaven and Glory, turn thy Face to the Wall, ſince thou haſt no private Room, and power out thy Soul before the Lord, and wait, yea wait earneſtly for, his Salvation.</p>
            <p>Do not fear the Fire, God will carry thee thorough it, it can only hurt thy Body, it ſhall not ſinge thy Soul. Though thy Fleſh and thy Bones be conſumed, thou wilt have many Mourners, and God, I hope will gather thine Aſhes, and grant thee a Glorious <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi> I want words to tell thee what the Joys of Heaven are, but thou wilt ſee, and feel, and taſt, and injoy them very ſhortly. I hope this day thou wilt be with the Lord, and all his bleſſed Saints, and glorious Angels in Paradiſe. She ſaid, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding my ill ſucceſs and many repulſes hitherto, yet I would not leave the Nurſe. I reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtill with my ſelf, who knoweth but that Grace may be given, and Satan may looſe his hold faſt, and the <hi>Prey may be taken out of the Paws of the ſpoiler, out of the jaws of the Devourer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Satan hath fallen as a flaſh of lightning before the Miniſtry of Gods Holy word, God hath him in a Chain, and though ſhe hath not liſtened to the voice of former admonitions, it may be ſhe ſhall now unto the laſt.</p>
            <p>Addreſſing my ſelf, therefore once again unto her, I told her, Nurſe, this is the laſt conference that ever I will have with thee on Earth about thy Soul, and nothing but my real ſence of its worth, and lothneſs that it ſhould be loſt for ever, would ever have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged me to it. That I got nothing but trouble, grief, and loſs of time thus to wait upon her, and not to be able to do good. I knew indeed my reward was with the Lord, and my work with my God, but yet I demanded this poor ſatisfaction of her now at parting,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:96502:39"/>that ſhe ſhould not ſend me away with the ſad thoughts of her damnation.</p>
            <p>To which ſhe very civilly replyed, <hi>Sir, I thank you for all your love to my Soul. I believe that what you have done and ſpoken, hath been in order to my Eternal good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well then, I added, ſhall you and I have a little private diſcourſe together? She agreed. Deſiring therefore the people to withdraw at a diſtance, I askt her in her Ear whether ſhe were Guilty or not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> (ſaith ſhe,) <hi>I will tell you all I know</hi> — Then ſtopt, at length the repeats again. <hi>I will tell you all I know</hi>—And then ſtops.</p>
            <p>Whereupon I told her, Nurſe, the Devil is leaving thee, God is coming in with mercy, do not now at the laſt hour refuſe it, tell me what you know of this buſineſs, and I aſſure thee upon the word of a Miniſter, that without thy conſent I will not diſcloſe it. Do not fear ſhame, ſhame the Devil, and give Glory to God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir, I confeſs, I did put the Spider into the Cup, and bad the Girl to ſquat it abroad; but it was a Fooliſh and vain word, I never intended any more hurt to my Miſtris, than I do to my own Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I believe ſhe ſpake the truth, for ſhe never intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed good to her Soul. Juſt like Doctor <hi>Lopez</hi> the <hi>Jew,</hi> who being convented before the Privy Councel, for attempting to Poyſon Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> told their Honors, <hi>That be loved the Queen better than be loved Chriſt. Yea,</hi> (ſaid a Noble Lord, <hi>thou telleſt the truth, for thou art a</hi> Jew, <hi>and loveſt both a like.</hi>)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Sir, I knew that this wicked Maid had an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to make away her Miſtris, and that ſhe did it; but I was loth to diſcover, and now I muſt ſuffer for her fault.</hi> I told her no, it was for her own; and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:96502:39"/>ſhe did not yet confeſs any thing to the purpoſe, all this I knew before, you muſt tell me as to your own hand and Guilt in this Murder. <hi>None! None at all Sir,</hi> that is her anſwer.</p>
            <p>But Nurſe, did you not tell ſuch a Miniſter that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited you in Goal, that you would conſider what he ſpoke unto you? at this ſhe changed countenance, paled and redded once and again, minced, aequivocat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and faltered in her expreſſions; but taking her in all her Evaſions, ſhe could not deny ſhe had promiſed him; and had conſidered of it, <hi>yet knew no guilt by her ſelf worthy of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Getting no ground here, I askt her concerning the Gold, her Brother took her for his Child, ſhe told me ſhe never had any from him. Why then did you ſpeak to Maſter <hi>W.</hi> to look after your Money, if you never had any, and be ſuch a Poor Woman?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir, I will without any diſſimulation tell yon all the Truth. My Brother acquainted me that there was Ten Pound in a Purſe hanging between the Vallance and the Wall of his Bed Chamber in</hi> Loo: <hi>Whereupon my Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band got an Horſe in</hi> Plymouth, <hi>Rode thither and brought it to me. So that I never had any of my Brother, but my Husband had.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, Nurſe, this may be as you ſay, though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly there was more; but how have you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of it? She replied, <hi>It is put out for my Child.</hi> I told her this is a very horrid Theft, the healer was as bad in the ſight of God as the ſtealer; that without Reſtitution there was no Remiſſion: That unleſs ſhe took ſome courſe for its being reſtored, ſhe could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſaved: That God would never bleſs it unto her Child: Yea, the very contrary, for it would be a ſnare and a curſe unto her, and an occaſion of deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction unto her, otherwiſe, innocent Child.</p>
            <p>And recollecting all my former diſcourſes and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:96502:40"/>to her, I preſſed with all poſſible earneſtneſs and importunity, not willfully to precipitate her ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell. That there were now but a few Sands in her Glaſs, a few breaths in her body, a few minutes in her time, that ſhe ſhould not play the Fool any longer; love the Devil, and hate God. The Devil had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready undone her, yet the Lord was willing to ſave her. He ſent me once again upon that errand, but if ſhe were reſolved to adhere unto her grand Enemy, and utterly forſake the Lord her beſt Friend, I was heartily ſorry for her, I foreſaw ſhe muſt <hi>Burn in Hell Everlaſtingly.</hi> That in the day of Judgment, I ſhould be a witneſs againſt her, and it would be a fearful thing, that God Almighty ſhould tell her; did not I ſend Miniſter upon Miniſter to Convert, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile and ſave thee? Did not this and that come unto thee, Woe and intreat thee with tears in their eyes, with fair and gentle, with terrible and amazing words to confeſs and give Glory to me, but thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not?</p>
            <p>Ah! Nurſe! Nurſe! What will you ſay unto the Lord then? She wept; and I wept for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
            <p>But recovering my ſelf, Woman ſaid I, do not flatter thy ſelf with falſe hopes of Life. For I fear thou keepeſt the Devils Counſel upon that account. Thou muſt die. All the world cannot ſave thee. Ere three hours be ſpent and gone, thou muſt be led unto the Gallows, and thence into Eternity. Oh! Hell! Hell! Hell! Woman is a place and ſtate of unſpeakable, of unſufferable horror and torment: Yet, Flee! Flee! Flee from it! Or thou art undone for ever.</p>
            <p>I now Love, Pitty, Intreat, and Pray for thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But if thou wilt be a Reprobate, a caſt away, I take God to witneſs, I have done my duty, my utmoſt to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:96502:40"/>ſave thee, Lord, ſaid I, lifting up my Eyes and Hands to Heaven, I am free of the ruin of this Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Let her Blood, and Damnation lie upon her own Head!</p>
            <p>And Nurſe, It is a very fearful thing to fall into the bands of the living God. The God to whom thou art going, is a conſuming Fire. Ah! Who can abide his anger? Who can ſtand before his indignation? None will compaſſionate thee at thy death. And in the day of Judgment, thou wilt be an abhorrency to all.</p>
            <p>All this wrought nothing upon her beſides tears: Still ſhe avows her innocency; and had I not had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable evidence of her guilt, poſſibly I might have been perſwaded ſhe was accuſed and condemned unjuſtly.</p>
            <p>After this I ſat down, and Mr. <hi>Collings,</hi> the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Miniſter of <hi>Charles</hi> Church coming in, he rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with her for a long time, as alſo my worthy Friend Mr. <hi>Sh.</hi> But a Marble Quarry affords no Water, nor her ſtony Heart one penitential Tear. At length all their pains being uſeleſs, ineffectual; and unſuccesful, we reſolved to try the Lord once more by Prayer, and ſee whether any mercy might be got out of Heaven for her.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Collings</hi> was our Mouth to God. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Perſons were upon their knees. Duty ended, I departed, and never ſpake more with her, till ſhe was upon the Ladder.</p>
            <p>ANd now ſhe is waited on to the Gallows.</p>
            <p>The Streets are crowded. The Major, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, and under Sheriff can hardly paſs for the throngs.</p>
            <p>The poor Maid is drawn on the Hurdle. The po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture ſhe lay in was on her left ſide, her Face in her
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:96502:41"/>Boſom, her Bible under her Arm, ſeeming like one dead, rather than alive.</p>
            <p>At length we are come, though ſlowly to the place of Execution. <hi>Plimouth</hi> was then naked of Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, the Town was eaſie to be taken, and the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to be plundered, if an Enemy had been at hand to have done it. <hi>Cat downe,</hi> the <hi>Lambhey, Cittadel, Turn-Chappel,</hi> and <hi>Cat-Water</hi> are preſt with multitudes. Some computed their number I'wenty thouſand. But Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, who at lived in Wars, and ſeen great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and therefore the moſt competent Judges in this caſe, eſtimated them at one half. I write within compaſs.</p>
            <p>The Maid being nailed to her Stake, and the Iron Hoop about her, and the Nurſe mounted upon the Ladder, ſhe deſires. that this Relator might now Pray with her.</p>
            <p>But it being thought requiſite that the eſtabliſhed Order of the Church ſhould be obſerved, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayers were firſt Commanded. Which having been read Audably, and with great Devotion from the By-ſtanders. The 51. <hi>Pſalm</hi> according to the Girls requeſt was ſung: Who (it was very obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,) joyned with the People, ſinging alſo her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>Now ſhe being queſtioned about her offence owns every particular thereof, it having been propounded to her in particulars. Owneth that the Nurſe bad her put it in; Only denieth the Depoſition of <hi>Scannels</hi> Wife, profeſſing that ſhe cannot remember it: Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth her hearty and unfeigned ſorrow for her ſin, not only becauſe it had ruined her Miſtreſſes and her ſelf; but principally, and eſpecially becauſe it was an high diſhonor to God, Father, Son, and Spirit, that it made her unworthy of his Favor and Bleſſing; yet ſhe profeſſed her Faith and Hope of Salvation, through
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:96502:41"/>the alone Merits of the Lord Jeſus, Into whoſe hands ſhe now commended her ſelf; and deſired to forgive all the World, and that Bloody Woman the Nurſe, who had drawn her into deſtruction; and added, that ſhe ſubmitted patiently to her death, becauſe ſhe had deſerved it. And ſaid, it was her wiſh, that all others would take warning by her Example; and taking this Relator by the hand, <hi>Sir,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>will you not pray with me? Did you not promiſe me yon would?</hi> And cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it with Tears, it was readily accorded.</p>
            <p>Silence being commanded, and every Perſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, there was this following Prayer conceived, and poured before the Lord in her behalf.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
               <body>
                  <p>MOſt Holy Lord God! The Righteous Judg of the whole World! Juſt in all thy Ways, and Holy in all Works! The great and terrible God! a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming Fire, and everlaſting burnings! How can ſuch ſinful chaff, and ſtubble as we are ſtand before thee? We muſt needs in a Moment be reduced unto Aſhes, if thou haſt not pitty on us. But bleſſed be thy Name, thou art a God of wonderful Love and Mercies, Thou haſt ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the World as to give thine only begotten Son to the death for us, that we believing in him ſhould not periſh but have everlaſting life.</p>
                  <p>We are greater Sinners than the Apoſtate Angels, and yet have greater Mercies afforded us, though they are better capacited to ſerve God than our ſelves, and never ſinned againſt thee but once, yet thou didſt utterly reject them, never gaveſt a Chriſt to them, nor to die for them; whereas thou haſt beſtowed him on us the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Perſons, Sons and Daughters of ſinful Adam, who have never ceaſed ſinning againſt thee.</p>
                  <p>We are all Sinners by Nature, and from our Youth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. We were conceived in ſin, and born in iniquity. Our Infancy, our Youth, and riper years have been all
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:96502:42"/>spent in the drudgery of ſin. We have broken all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of our God in heart, thought, word, and deed; ſinned againſt the Law, and againſt the Goſpel; againſt all the means uſed by our God to reclaim, and to reform us. We have despiſed the beſt of Mercies, and deſerved the worſt of Judgments, yea to be burnt up with unquenchable flames, as this poor, wretched Malefactor is now ready to be with thoſe that are temporal. But hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto thou haſt spared and reprieved us, and given us space for Repentance, and waiteſt to be gracious to us, and biddeſt us, ſeek thee O our God, whileſt thou mayeſt be found, and call upon thee whileſt thou art near, it forſake our ungodlineſs, and to forego all our wickedneſs, and thou wouldeſt abundantly pardon; yea thou art ſo gracious, as to bid and incourage us to Pray for others, with promiſes of Audience and Acceptance.</p>
                  <p>This emboldens us to make our addreſſes to thee for this poor <hi>condemned Creature,</hi> ready to be executed. We confeſs for her, and ſhe doth acknowledg for her ſelf, Lord! her great and grievous offences, that ſhe hath been a Rebel againſt thee all her days, lived in ſin, neglected duty, neglected getting the ſaving knowledg of God, and acquaintance with thee; that ſhe hath not hearkened to the voice of God speaking from his holy Word unto her; but liſtned readily unto the Temptations and Suggeſtion of the Devil, a Murderer from the beginning, and by whoſe enticements ſhe hath embrewed her hands in Blood, in the guilt of innocent Blood of her Relation and Superiors, which crys to Heaven for vengeance againſt her. Lord! ſhe cannot ſtand before the Juſtice of Men. Ah! how unable is ſhe to ſubſiſt at the Bar of God? Man hath juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contemned her, and the Lord might juſtly damn her, and that to all Eternity. The wages of her ſin is death, death Temporal, and Eternal.</p>
                  <p>But Lord! though ſhe is miſerable, thou art merciful; though ſhe is full of ſins, thou art full of pardons; though
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:96502:42"/>ſhe is helpleſs in her ſelf, yet in thee Lord, is ſhe not hopeleſs. Bleſſed be God that hath opened a Door of hope for her in the Reſurrection of Chriſt Jeſus, who was delivered to the death for her ſins, and roſe again from the dead, that ſhe might be juſtified. Thy Free guift in Chriſt Jeſus is Eternal Life, Oh! How ſweet is thy mercy?</p>
                  <p>Suffer us, Bleſſed Father! in all humility to plead with thee in her behalf, Oh, That thou wouldeſt be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to her! she is thy Creature, the work of thine hands, do not deſtroy her! She is the purchaſe of thy Sons blood, Oh, Let him not looſe her! Chriſt died for her, Oh, Let him not die in vain for her! Therefore ſave her! Her ſins are many, but thy mercies are infinitely more, her ſins are Bloody, Crimſon, Scarlet, and crying ſins. but the blood of Jeſus cleanſeth from all ſins. Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by her cryeth down Vengeance on her. But yet, dear Lord! Hear! Oh hear the lowder outcries of thy Sons blood for her! She is, if ever any, an object wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of pitty, not from any worth in her, but becauſe of her miſery. If God do not help her, who will? Who can? Men and Angels cannot ſave her, but Jeſus Chriſt can. He is able. And Beſſed be thy name, ſweet Jeſu! Thou art willing alſo even to the worſt and utmoſt to ſave.</p>
                  <p>Thou art an Almighty, and All ſufficient Saviour, thine arm is not ſhortened, thy Grace is not exhauſted. Oh, Magnifie thy Grace now, even now upon her! Thou haſt ſaid, that the weary, the heavy laden ſhould come unto thee, and thou wouldeſt give them reſt: And that ſuch as come unto thee, though the greateſt ſinners, thou wouldeſt not caſt out 'Tis late indeed that ſhe comes unto thee, but not too late. Truth Lord! Late Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is ſeldom true, but yet true Repentance is never too late. Bitter late than never.</p>
                  <p>Thou haſt given us one inſtance, one example of the Thief on the Croſs ſaved at the Eleventh, at the laſt hour ſave one, 'tis but one, that we ſhould not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume;
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:96502:43"/>and yet one, that we. ſhould not deſpair; Oh Lord, ſhe will not deſpair of thy mercy, that were a greater ſin than all the reſt that ſhe hath committed. Now Lord, though late ſhe comes unto thee, ſhe throws her ſelf at thy Feet, and we thy poor Servants come unto thee, and proſtrate our ſelves at thy fleet for her: Oh! Do not caſt her out of thy ſight! Oh! Let her not be Damned, but ſaved! This is a true and faithful ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, worthy of all acceptation, moſt worthy of hers, and ſhe accepts of it, and reſts upon it, and truſts unto it, that Jeſus Chriſt came into the World to ſave ſinners, <hi>Of whom ſhe is chief,</hi> Thou art willing that all ſhould be ſaved: Therefore thou art willing ſhe ſhould be ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alſo. Thou haſt put theſe words into her mouth, and into our mouths for her. <hi>That if Jeſus Chriſt, hath not merits enough to ſave her, ſhe, and we alſo will be contented that ſhe ſhould be Damned for, ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But Bleſſed be our God! The merits of our Saviour are Infinite, Oh! Lord, make application of them unto her poor Soul. Oh! Take away for Chriſts ſake all her ſins! Blot out her iniquities at a Cloud, and her Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions as a thick Cloud, Though her ſins have abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto her Condemnation, yet let thy grace much more, infinitely more abound unto her juſtification. Enter not into judgment with her, Oh Lord! Deliver her from blood guiltineſs, Oh God, thou God of her salvation! And her Tongue, and our mouths ſhall ſing aloud of Chriſts Righteouſneſs and of thy Faithfulneſs.</p>
                  <p>Oh, take away whatſoever may hinder the Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of thy Love, favor, and salvation unto her! Purge ſin out of her! Give a broken, contrite, and truly Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent heart unto her! She is Mourning for her ſin, and miſery: Oh, waſh her in the blood of the Lamb, in that Fountain opined for ſin and for Uncleanneſſes, in the lavor of Regeneration! Oh, ſanctifie, and renew her by thy Holy Spirit! Take away all the ſpots and blots of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:96502:43"/>her ſin! Though ſhe be defiled and deformed with innumerable and thoſe the moſt abominable, yet canſt thou renſe and cleanſe her in a moment. No unclean thing ſhall enter into thy Kingdom. Without Holineſs none can ſee the Lord. Now the Lord Sanctifie her throughout, in her whole Soul, Body and Spirit.</p>
                  <p>And though ſhe hath been by the wiles of the Devil cheated of her life, and is now to ſuffer Juſtly for her evil deeds, give her to bear patiently the indignation of her God, becauſe ſhe hath ſinned againſt thee, and to accept of the puniſhment of her iniquity! Though ſhe muſt burn in Temporal flames, yet let her not burn in Everlaſting flames! Oh, Let the ſtreams of Chriſts blood quench out the flames of thy wrath! Though ſhe die in Earth, Lord! Save her from Hell! Oh, Give her Faith, the Faith of Gods elect! And the Lord ſtrengthen her Faith! Oh, Confirm her hope! Oh, Give her to abound in hope through thy Holy Ghoſt given to her! Oh, Grant that Faith, Hope, and patience may have their perfect work in her.</p>
                  <p>Give in ſome token, ſome pledge of thy good will unto her, if it be thy good pleaſure! Oh, revive, ſupport, and comfort her drooping Spirits! Though ſhe be in the Valley and ſhaddow of death; do not forſake her! Oh, do not forſake her! Say unto her, thou art her Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on! Tell her, that after ſhe hath ſuffered a little while, ſhe ſhall be with thy ſelf in Heaven, perfect with thee in Glory! Say unto her as unto the Thief upon the Croſs, this day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe!</p>
                  <p>Oh, keep off Satan from her! He is never more buſie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>han when thy poor Worms are weakeſt, and leaſt able to defend themſelves from him. Lord Jeſu! Fight for her againſt him! Keep her pretious and immortal Soul from him! Oh, Be with her now in theſe her laſt agonies. Give thy Holy Angels to wait upon her, and in that very moment that her Soul ſhall go out of her Body, let thoſe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:96502:44"/>Glorious Angels carry it into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome! Into thy hands do we commend her. Into thy hands doth ſhe commit her Spirit Dear Jeſu! Save it! For thou haſt loved, redeemed, and died for it! And now Lord, though earth will looſe a bloody Sinner, yet let Heaven be augmented by one saint more!</p>
                  <p>O Look down from Heaven, the Habitation of thy Holineſs and Glory upon this numerous Aſſembly! Oh, let them not be idle Spectators of theſe dreadful Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences. Oh, That they may be Ordinances for this good, for their Converſion and Reformation! Oh, That every Soul, that is gazing here may ſmite upon his Breaſt, and lament that Univerſal corruption which is in our nature, and the woful effects of our ſin. Sin having once conceived, bringeth forth death.</p>
                  <p>We have the root of the matter in us, the very cauſes of thoſe ſins, for which theſe Malefactors ſuffer, had we the ſame temptations we might be Guilty of the like tranſgreſſions. And were it not for the Cords and Curbs of thy Reſtraining Grace, we ſhould be in their Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Bleſſed be God we are not! 'Tis thou only that haſt made us to differ. Oh, That all Maſters of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, Parents of Children, would ſee that they in their own Perſons, and with their Families do ſerve the Lord! Oh, Let there be no 'Prayerleſs Families, no uncatechized Children in this Place!</p>
                  <p>Look once more we pray thee, with mercy upon this thy poor Creature! She is very low, very miſerable, yearn upon her with bowels of compaſſion, and embrace her with arms of everlaſting lave! Be her God and her Guide unto death, and her Saviour from everlaſting death!</p>
                  <p>And all we beg, in, and for the ſake of our dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who ſits on the Right hand making interceſſion for her, and for us. Hear us
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:96502:44"/>for his ſake, and gratiouſly anſwer us, and do abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for her, and us, beyond what we can ask or think! To him, with thy ſelf Holy Father, and Eternal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, be Everlaſting Glory, Dominion, Praiſe, and Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Prayer being ended, I lifted up my hands over her, and ſaid, <hi>Anne,</hi> the Lord bleſs thee, and keep thee! The Lord make his Face to ſhine upon thee, and be gracious to thee! The Lord lift up the light of his countenance upon thee, and give thee Peace! And if thy Repentance be true, and thy peace made with God, and our Prayers heard, as I hope they all are, death wont be terrible unto thee. Now Farewel Life, welcome Death. God will ſend his Holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in a Fiery Chariot to Convey thy Soul into Heaven.</p>
            <p>THis poor wretch weeping, and wringing me by the hand, <hi>Sir,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>I am never able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite you for all your labor of love, care and pains about the Salvation of my pretious Soul; but the Lord. will, I hope. The Lord reward you! The Lord recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe you for all theſe kindneſſes! I thank you with all my Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as I was departing from her, ſhe helpake me, <hi>Sir, pray intreat for me, that I may not be put to too much torture.</hi> I anſwered her in broken words and tears (for few there refrained.) That I would do my utmoſt endeavor to prevent it: And turning my ſelf to the Gentlemen in Authority. Gentlemen, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> temper abhors Cruelty, ſhow ſame Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els to this poor Creature. I need not intreat it, there was ſuch a Clowd of grief ſitting upon all their
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:96502:45"/>Faces, and ſo much tenderneſs and companion, that they would have done their utmoſt to have hindred it.</p>
            <p>Two—went to the Maid, and asked her what Faith and what Repentance were. And one of them proceeded to inſtruct her in the nature of Faith, that it was to take Chriſt as Lord and King, and to ſubmit unto all his Laws, to be Governed by them, and in particular to this of ſuffering the puniſhment inflicted on her for her ſin.</p>
            <p>At which putting them off with my Hand, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen; do not trouble her, 'tis unſeaſonable now to Catechize her in Doctrinals; ſhe ſtands in need of ſome Soveraign Cordials to revive and ſupport her drooping Spirit in theſe her laſt Agonies with death, and conflicts with the Devil.</p>
            <p>And Addreſſing my ſelf once again unto her, <hi>Anne</hi> ſaid I, fear not, but caſt thy ſelf upon the everlaſting mercies of God in the blood of Chriſt Jeſus, and thou ſhalt be ſaved. Since thou muſt die, die upon this, that Jeſus Chriſt came into the World to ſave ſinners, of whom thou art chief. And 'twill be but a quarter of an hour, and thou ſhalt be freed from all ſins and torments. Say. Into thy hands I commit my Spirit. Lord ſave it! For thou haſt died for it. Lord Jeſu, thou Son of <hi>David</hi> have mercy upon me! Oh, Thou Lamb of God receive my Soul!</p>
            <p>I left her, expecting no anſwer. The Rope is now drawn cloſe unto her Neck, and the Hangman would have ſet Fire unto the Fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ze before ſhe was ſtrangled but ſome more charitable and tender-hearted, cryed to him to take away the Block from under her Feet; which having done, ſhe ſoon fell down, and expired in a Trice.</p>
            <p>And it was obſervable, that all the skill and diligence
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:96502:45"/>of the Executioner and his Aſſiſtants, could not make either Powder, Wood, or Fewel to take fire; till ſhe had been dead a Quarter of an hour; as alſo, that as ſoon as the fire was kindled, the Wind which blew be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the back of the Nurſe, immediately ſhifted, and drove the ſmoke full in her Face; as if God had ſpoken to her, The Smoke of my Fury, and Flames of my Fiery Vengeance are now Riding upon the Wings of the Wind towards thee.</p>
            <p>And now for Two hours, the Nurſe feeds her eyes, and feaſts her thoughts with the ſad ſpectacle of this poor Maids burning.</p>
            <p>The flames being well allayed, ſeveral Miniſters, and worthy Gentlemen indeavor yet the Repentance, Converſion, and Saving of her Soul. But All ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds as formerly. She denies her guilt; pleads her Innocency, accuſeth Judg, Jury, Witneſſes, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and all of her Murther; that ſhe is Murthered, that they take away her Life unjuſtly: Nay, that they kill too; ſhe is with Child, expects to be delivered about Midſummer. What will you Murther one that is unborn? And a great deal more of the like ſtuff.</p>
            <p>That ſhe was not with Child we heard evidenced upon Oath at her condemnation. And a skilful Hand-Woman, ſearching her but a night before her Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, could never diſcover any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>Moſt probable the true ground of all her denials, was a fooliſh hope of Life; the Hangman as it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly noiſed, having promiſed never to execute her. Whatever familiarities had paſt between them Two in Jail, I know not. This is certain, the Hangman brought the under Sheriff to terms juſt as they were leaving <hi>Plymouth,</hi> and going to the place of Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And the Girl being diſpatched, he ran away with the Halter under the Clifts; and when he was brought back, lay aſleep at the Foot of the Gallows,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:96502:46"/>or at leaſt pretended ſleep, and ſo deſerted Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
            <p>Beſides another Accident intervened, which put a ſtop for a time, and had it not been prudently and preſently compoſed upon the place, would have to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally ſuſpended, for that day at leaſt, her Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>All theſe Circumſtances jumping in one upon the other, contributed to the ſtrengthening of her Heart in the falſe hopes of Life. For what ſhe would have, it was an eaſie matter to perſwade her to believe and hope.</p>
            <p>But at length ſhe hath worn out all patience both of God, and Man. And the Halter is faſtened to the Gibber, and put about her Neck. Now Miniſters ply their work with her, becauſe ſhe is upon the brink of Deſtruction, and in view of Hell.</p>
            <p>No ſin ſhe acknowledged, no guilt as to the Fact for which ſhe is condemned. Indeed ſhe confeſſeth, <hi>She had been a Swearer, Lier, and Sabbath breaker,</hi> but none others trouble her. As to Money that her Brother ſtole, and was in hers, or her Husbands hands, ſhe now chargeth upon a dead Perſon, having wronged her in her life, the muſt miſchief her at her death too. No Bond, nor Bill can ſhe produce, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing under the Deceaſed's hand can ſhe ſhow for her having received it; yet doth ſhe charge Mr. <hi>W.</hi> to look that it be reſtored unto the right Owner.</p>
            <p>Miniſters however lament her deplorable condition, eſpecially ſince juſt as ſhe is going out of the World, ſhe cryes, <hi>Judg and Revenge my cauſe, O Lord!</hi> Which made this Relator tell her, He now ſaw, what he formerly feared, <hi>viz.</hi> That God was departed from her, that the Devil was already in her heart, for he ſat upon her tongue, that troops of Devils were upon the Ladder by her, all gaping for her; and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:96502:46"/>in a few moments, they would have her wretched Soul into Hell with them; and then, and there ſhe would be ſoon ſenſible of her madneſs in dying with a Lye in her Mouth, and confeſs, and mourn for her folly and madneſs in rejecting Heaven and Salvation, but it would be too late, and to no purpoſe: For her condition, whatever it might be here, would infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be there unalterable, and irreverſible.</p>
            <p>That ſhe was going into a Lake of Fire and Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone there to be tormented for ever and ever; and when ſhe was in the midſt of thoſe Eternal torments, ſhe would remember that I had told her of it.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Pſalm</hi> was called, and part of the Twenty fifth ſung. Never did I ſee but one in that heavy condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Whilſt the people ſing, ſhe cries and weeps bitterly, the very terrors of death are upon her, ſhe cries as if her Heart would break. Indeed her Soul was overwhelmed with unmeaſurable horrors and fears; ſhe had no mind to die, nor could ſhe be vouchſafed Life. What hopes could ſhe have in her departure, who never laid any ſollid baſis for good hopes during life?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Pſalm</hi> is now sung out, and yet is ſhe ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to confeſs, but it is as good ſpeak to the ſtones, or to the Deaf Adder, that ſtops his ear, ſhe will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be charmed, let the Charmers Charm never ſo wiſely.</p>
            <p>At laſt being demanded whether ſhe would have any Prayers, or any Perſon Pray for her, ſhe ſaid yes, and pointed to this Relator, deſiring him to perform that Office for her: Who replied, that he was moſt willing to ſerve and ſave her Soul: But in as much as ſhe made no Confeſſion of her Crying ſins of Murther, and of her Theft and Uncleanneſs, and other Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies whereof me knew her ſelt Guilty, he durſt not take the name of God in vain tor her ſake; Beſides
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:96502:47"/>he ſhould but tempt God to ask a pardon for her, Who reſolved never to take it upon Gods Terms.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, if ſhe would be yet ingenious, and give Glory to God by adoring his Juſtice, and ſhameing her ſelf, and renouncing her ſin and the Devil, there Was no perſon more willing to pray with her, and pray for her than himſelf.</p>
            <p>To which ſhe making no reply, Mr. <hi>R.</hi> the Miniſter conceived a pithy and pertinent Prayer, lamenting the depravedneſs of our Nature, the horribleneſs of Gods wrath, the poſſibility of Salvation refuſed by deſperate ſinners, and as we feared in particular by this Malefactor his dear Siſter now ready to be turned over. He petitioned that if it were not yet too late, that God would give her Repentance, and break her ſtony heart, and cauſe her to glorifie him at the laſt by an ingenious and full Confeſſion.</p>
            <p>Prayer being ended, ſhe is once again asked, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe would confeſs. But being obſtinate in her refuſals, ſhe prayed for her ſelf in the words of the lords Prayer, ſaid the Creed; and being yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to Remember the merciful nature of God, who would ſave her, as we yet hoped, provided ſhe would come unto his Terms of Confeſſion and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>She tells us. <hi>She cannot confeſs that whereof is not Guilty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being asked whether ſhe could die in Charity with her Witneſſes and Accuſers. She ſaid, <hi>I forgive all the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And a while after, without any viſible tokens of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Grace, or Devotion, without any obſervable preparedneſs or willingneſs for death, by any of thoſe many Divines that had painfully dealt with her, or Chriſtians that beheld her, ſhe was turned
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:96502:47"/>off the Ladder, and went into that other World. She went out like the Snuff of a Candle, leaving a ſtench behind her.</p>
            <p>And if it be asked, what is become of her Soul?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, the Queſtion is idle, needleſs, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curious, and unprofitable, 'tis not for ſaucy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, poor crawling Earth-worms, (ſuch at our ſelves are) to pry into the deep ſecrets of Gods E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Counſels, nor to peep into the ſacred Ark of his bottomleſs decrees. Theſe inſcrutable purpoſes of God by reaſon of their inexplicable difficulties will amaze and puzle us; nor can we ever poſſibly attain unto any infallible certainty or ſatisfaction concerning her. I know the abſolute and uncontroulable Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of Divine Grace and mercies, and that God can come in, if he pleaſe, between the Bridge and Water, the Cup and the Lip. But who can inform, or aſſure me that God did ſo to her? She is gone unto her Judge, hath undergone her Doom; and if ſhe be ſaved, it is a Thouſand mercies unto the World, that the World neither doth, nor can know it.</p>
            <p>But did ſhe not proteſt her Innocency to the very laſt.</p>
            <p>I know ſhe did, and is ſhe Innocent becauſe ſhe ſaid ſo? Dying perſons are indeed to be credited: But then they muſt be perſons of credit and ſerious; and if Condemned Malefactors, ſuch as are moſt Eminent and exemplary for their Repentance. Can any one Man or Woman living, that Converſt with her from firſt to laſt, from her Impriſonment to her Execution, avow upon her knowledge, that ſhe ſaw ſo much as one poor token of a broken heart, of a ſincere Penitent in her? Produce it, and it ſhall be Thankfully accepted.</p>
            <p>Had ſhe been Innocent, ſhe could not have been ſo much concerned for life as ſhe was? I told her in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:96502:48"/>
               <hi>'Plymouth</hi> and <hi>Exon,</hi> and ſhe was told the ſame by a Reverend Divine, that Innocency was a Wall of Braſs, it would carry a Perſon above the fear of Death, make her to outbrave Death; ſhe could go trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly into the preſence of the Eternal Judg, and bleſs him that ſhe was condemned unjuſtly.</p>
            <p>Beſides, her Innocence as to this Fact, would have ingaged her to a more curious and exact ſcrutiny in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her life paſt, to have found out the true cauſe of Gods anger in ſhortning her days, and to a moſt holy life, and religious preparation of her Soul for death, during the whole time of her impriſonment. None of which ſhe had done; unleſs looſeneſs, prophaneneſs, and uncleanneſs muſt be expounded, and taken for it.</p>
            <p>Finally, I lookt upon her as a deſperate and Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne wretch, and told her it was no new thing to find her ſuch. 'Tis no new thing tor the worſt of ſinners to be deſperate. Were not <hi>Cain, Saul, Abimelech, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitophel</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> deſperate? This Relator heard a man Condemned to be Hanged, utter upon the Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe words.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, I value not my life of a Ruſh, I fear not death; and without any more Ceremonies or ado, (and Soldiers are none of the moſt Religious.) He willfully leapt off of the Ladder at <hi>Crimble-paſſage:</hi> Where had not others ſhown his body more mercy than he did hi own Soul, he might have periſht ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly.</p>
            <p>I know not whether ſhe had as much Courage. Sure I am, Death never ſtruck unto her Spirits; till the <hi>Pſalm</hi> was a Singing, and it was a doleful Tune unto her. Her heart was then up in her mouth. If it were not broke with the ſence of ſin, and near ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of Divine wrath, it was with the very hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of death. Others Sang, ſhe did but howl and yell. Methought the expreſſions of her grief, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:96502:48"/>vehemency of her paſſions, raiſed ſtrange reſentments and compaſſions in the Spectators.</p>
            <p>One, and but one have I known in her condition, a big and tall Fellow, that upon the ſcore of his ſtrength, could have affrighted the King of Terrors: Yet after Sentence (and for Burglary was he Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced unto death,) his heart failed him, his Spirits ſunk, his Soul died within him: All his Language, and that too in groans and Floods of Tears, with blubbered Cheeks and wringed hands, was: <hi>I ſhall die! I ſhall die! I ſhall die! I ſhall die! Woe is me! I ſhall die! I ſhall die!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though I came to him into the Jail, took him by the hand, intreated him upon my knees, not to be ſo much concerned for the loſs of his Natural Life: But to look after another, a better Life, after the life of his miſerable Soul; Yet no Arguments, no motives could prevail upon him. He was Deaf in that ear. A ſtone might have heard and anſwered, but this wretch would give none other anſwer, than, <hi>I ſhall die! I ſhall die! Woe is me! I ſhall die! I ſhall die!</hi> The terrors of death, like an opiate Medicine, had quite ſtupified him, that he could not liſten unto the beſt Counſels for his Souls welfare.</p>
            <p>But what and if this vile woman had been Guilty of ſome other Capital Crimes? I know of the dead rue beſt muſt be ſpoken; but then thoſe dead perſons ſhould not be Impenitent Criminals.</p>
            <p>It is no pleaſure to me, no pleaſing task to Rake in Dunghils. Would to God all Vices were Buried together with hers, though under the Gibbet! It were no difficult matter, nay a man might with a wet Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, prove her Guilty of ſoul and frequent Adulteries, of Debauching Young perſons, of proſtituting her ſelf in Priſon, are theſe no Capital offences? Let them not be! What meant ſhe by thoſe words unto
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:96502:49"/>the Girl, that to her knowledg a little Poyſon in Cream had made one away in leſs time than you could go from her Matters Houſe to the Gate.</p>
            <p>I am apt to think that ſhe would not confeſs this Murder leſt ſome other might out alſo. There was a ſhrewed <hi>Item</hi> in her <hi>Exon</hi> acknowledgment, That ſhe knew ſhe ſhould be damned, though not for this Crime.</p>
            <p>It brings to my remembrance a Story which I had from Mr. <hi>B. Cl.</hi> a very holy Man of God, a Reverend Miniſter of the Goſpel, (who if yet in the Land of the living, is one of the moſt Ancient Laborers in the Lords Vineyard in this Weſtern Dioceſs,) that in his younger days when he was Miniſter of <hi>Petrocks</hi> by the Caſtle of <hi>Dartmouth,</hi> he was ſent to Viſit and Pray with a dying Man, under very much trouble of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>His caſe was this, Sir, ſaid he unto the Miniſter, about Seven months ſince, as I was walking to <hi>Buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cow,</hi> I met a Camerade of mine, who had gone to Sea about a fortnight ſince, and taking him by the hand, wondring at his arrival, I ſaid, VVhat cheat Mate? What makes thee return ſo ſoon, and look ſo Pale? I am dead quoth this <hi>Spectrum.</hi> Dead Man, and yet walk, and talk? Yes, ſaith he, I am dead. I was took ſick ſhortly upon my going to Sea; and died this day, and about an hour ſince, ſo many Leagues off, was I thrown overboard.</p>
            <p>Now I deſire thee to go home, and tell my Wiſe of it, and to open my Coffer, and ſhow her my Will, and ſee my Legacies paid; which having promiſed to do for him, at parting he added, <hi>And at for that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs between thee and me, that thou well woteſt off, I charge thee, that thou never speak of it to any Man living, for if thou doſt, I will in that very moment tear thee in a thouſand pieces.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:96502:49"/>
            <p>Now Sir, this lies heavy, heavy upon my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Fain would I declare it, It is upon my Tongue, but I cannot. And why can you not? Oh Sir, do not you ſee him? Do not you ſee him? Look how terrible he is! There he is juſt againſt me. Oh! how doth he threaten me? I would tell you, but I dare not, And whatever arguments this Reverend Perſonage could uſe unto the ſick Man, he could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bring him to a Confeſſion; but he pines away un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his terrors, and horrors; till at laſt not being able to ſubſiſt any longer by reaſon of them, he died.</p>
            <p>Whether there be any parallel between the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this Man, and Woman, I leave it unto my Readers judgment.</p>
            <p>The poor Girl, at her Death, at the very point of Death charged her with it. This <hi>Philip Cary</hi> her ſelf confeſſed before the Major of <hi>Plymouth</hi> at her Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and the very day before her Execution to this Relator, that ſhe knew of it. And is ſhe Innocent? We have reaſon to believe the confeſſion of a Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, before the denial of a ſtubborn, and impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent VVoman.</p>
            <p>Beſides, ſhe had a very fair trial before the Judg. There were no leſs than Nineteen VVitneſſes that gave in their Evidence to his Lordſhip, and the Grand Jury upon Oath againſt her. Yet ſhe ſaith, Not guilty: Yea, and takes it to her death, that ſhe is Innocent, knew nothing of Poyſon.</p>
            <p>But what if all this be nothing but Lyes, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture? VVhat if evidence appears againſt her after death, and that ſhe did both know of it, and buy the Poyſon alſo?</p>
            <p>Reader I will not amuſe thee, call thine Eyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what follows, and thou wilt be in ſo me mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſatisfied.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="examination">
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:96502:50"/>
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Wife of <hi>Thomas</hi> Webb of <hi>Plymouth,</hi> in the County of <hi>Devon.</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riner, had, and taken at <hi>Plymouth,</hi> by, and before the Worſhipful <hi>William Weeks,</hi> Gentleman, one of his Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace within the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough of <hi>Plymouth,</hi> on her Corporal Oath the Seventh day of <hi>April, Anno Domini 1676.</hi>
            </head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>THe ſaid Examinant ſaith, That about a week before, <hi>Philip</hi> the Wife of <hi>Richard Cary</hi> of <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> was committed to <hi>Plimouth</hi> Priſon, on ſuſpition for the Poyſoning of <hi>Elizabeth Weeks,</hi> and <hi>Mary Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelley;</hi> This Examinant, <hi>on a Saturday Evening,</hi> when the Candles were lighted being at the Houſe of <hi>John Vallacke</hi> Apothecary in <hi>Plymouth,</hi> there came into the ſaid Mr, <hi>Vallacks</hi> ſhop, a VVoman (who was a ſtranger unto this Examinant,) and deſired the ſaid Mr. <hi>Vallacks</hi> Boy to give her a Penny worth of <hi>Mercury,</hi> as ſhe called it, and ſaid ſhe was haſty: That accordingly the ſaid Boy, delivered unto the ſaid VVoman the ſaid <hi>Mercury,</hi> (as ſhe called it) <hi>in a white Paper.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that about a week after, that the ſaid <hi>Philip Cary</hi> being committed unto the ſaid Priſon as afore ſaid, this Examinant went to the VVindow of the Priſon, and ſaw her, and ſhe believes that the ſaid <hi>Philip Cary</hi> was the ſame VVoman, which ſo fetched the ſaid <hi>Mercury</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Signum dicta.</hi> E. VV. <hi>Elizabeth Webb.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Poſſibly you will ask, VVhy had not this VVoman given in her Evidence, being ſo material, before her death? I anſwer, She is of age, Let her ſpeak for her ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:96502:50"/>
            <p>REader, by this time, I believe thou art well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied; Sure if thou be not, I am. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever at parting, let me ask thee one Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, VVhat art thou? A Maſter, or a Servant? A Parent, or a Child? In what Relation ſtandeſt thou? Inferior, or Superior.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> If thou be a. Child, or Servant; Receive Wiſdom, receive Inſtruction.</head>
               <p n="1">1. BEware of little ſins, you generally make no rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning of them. Your vain Thoughts, your idle Words, your envious and malicious Imaginations, your froward Replies and Anſwers again, your undutiful and diſobedient Carriages to Parents, to your Maſters, and Miſtreſſes, theſe are counted by you little ſins. But what and if God call them great ſins? VVhoſe opinion and judgment ſhall we take concerning the nature and evil of ſin. Yours, or Gods?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My dear Youth!</hi> Read, and Ponder that Text of Scripture, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall break one of theſe leaſt Commandments, and ſhall teach Men ſo, he ſhall be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the leaſt in the kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Math. 5.19.</p>
               <p>I muſt tell you, and you ſhall find it by woful expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that little ſins allowed, make way for great ſins. A little Thief creeping in at the VVindows, may open the Door to great Ones. A little Sin is as mortal, as damnable as a great one. A little Leak undiſcerned, may ſink Ship, Men, and Goods. A Ponyard ſhall ſtab a Man to death, as well as a Rapier. A Piſtol can kill, as well as a Cannon. Little ſins fill up the meaſure of your ſins; one very little ſin may do it. Cyphers in themſelves ſignifie nothing; but added unto figures, how do they raiſe
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:96502:51"/>the ſum? A Conſonant of it ſelf may be a Mute, make no ſound, but joyned with a Vowel may make a roaring noiſe.</p>
               <p>Thoſe which you call little ſins may fill up the Sum, and ſeal up the Account, and make a roaring Noiſe againſt you in Heaven. Your thought-ſins never act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but intended, are juſt like a Grain caſt on a piece of Gold, or a light Feather upon an heap, they may turn the Scales, and bring down upon you Eternal Vengeance. The <hi>Sodomites</hi> had committed many ſins, and God had paſſed them by very graciouſly; at laſt <hi>they would have ſinned,</hi> and are puniſhed with Hell out of Heaven for <hi>the ſin of their Wills,</hi> a ſin in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by them, though never committed. <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.9.11.24.</p>
               <p n="2">2. My dear Youth, beware of wicked Company. <hi>Bleſſed is the Man that walketh not in the Counſel of the Ungodly, nor ſtandeth in the way of Sinners, nor ſitteth in the Seat of the Scornful.</hi> Pſal. 1.1. Look upon wicked Company as Plaguy Perſon, and ſhun them as you would thoſe who had the Plague of God upon them. VVhen <hi>Corah,</hi> and his rebellious Crue were ſwallowed up alive by the yawning Earth, and went down quick into Hell, <hi>All</hi> Iſrael <hi>that were round about them, fled at the cry of them; for they ſaid, leſt the Earth ſwallow us up alſo.</hi> Num. 33.34.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Son, if Sinners intice thee, conſent thou not; if if they ſay come with us, let us lay wait for Blood, let us lurk privily for the Innocent without Cauſe; let us ſwallow them up alive as the Grave: We ſhall find all pretious ſubſtance, we ſhall fill our Houſes with ſpoil. Caſt in thy lot among us, let us all have one Purſe. My Son, walk not thou in the way with them; refrain thy Foot from their path: For their Feet run to evil, they lay wait for their own Blood. You lurk privily for
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:96502:51"/>the deſtruction of your own lives.</hi> Companions in ſin, will be Companions in Hell. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.10. to 19.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Flee the ſins of youth, vanity and ſelf-conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, raſhneſs, pride, and oſtentation, hot blood, Fiery, and vindictive paſſions, noyſome, filthy, and fleſhly luſts, diſobedience and brutiſh obſtinacy, ſelf-love, lying, idleneſs and intemperance, neglect of your Souls, forgetfulneſs of God and of your latter end. Sins of youth, have been an Hell to Gods aged Saints. <hi>Thou writeſt bitter things againſt me, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membereſt the iniquities of my Youth,</hi> Job 13.26. The ſins of your green years will be a ſtock of ſorrows for your Gray Hairs. Young Colts muſt be tamed and broken. A young Penitent is better than an aged Sinner. Holyneſs in youth will give you peace in death; 1 <hi>King</hi> 14.13. and 2 <hi>Chronicles</hi> 34.27.28.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Study diligently and practice conſcientiouſly the duty of thy place, calling and Relation. Art thou a Child? Learn and perform the duty of a Child. Art thou a Servant? Learn and perform the duty of a Servant, ſubmit to Catechizing, do not count it a thing beneath thee. Subjection to Gods Ordinances is thy dignity and Glory. Honor thy Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thy Maſter and Miſtreſs is the Firſt Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with promiſe, if you do not, you are ſelf-Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, you cut your own Throats, and ſhorten the days of your life.</p>
               <p>I have read of a Young man Hanged at Four and twenty years, whoſe Curled Black Locks upon the Gallows inſtantly turned white, many inquiring into the cauſe of ſuch a ſtrange event: A Grave Divine aſſigned this reaſon, had this young man been dutiful to his Parents, Obedient to his Superiors, he might
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:96502:52"/>have lived ſo long, till that in the courſe of nature, his Black Hairs had become White.</p>
               <p n="5">5. When tempted to any ſcandalous ſin, tending to the hurt of thy Neighbor, and the Temptation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth on thee, diſcloſe it without any more ado to ſome Godly Miniſter. This daſheth the temptation to pieces, and will contribute as you ſhall find by experience, wonderfully unto your peace and ſafety.</p>
               <p>Had this poor Girl, when firſt aſſaulted, detected the Devils Counſel, poſſibly ſhe had never been drawn out to Murder.</p>
               <p>I knew one in the like Caſe, that after I had preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the miſchievouſneſs of thoughts, and of the ready way to quell and ſubdue their violence and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuoſity, by taking Ghoſtly Counſel from a Spiritual Guide, came and diſcovered unto me with a ſtood of Tears a long imended purpoſe of Murder, and by the bleſſing of God on a Religious uſe of Holy Counſels was afterward delivered from that Helliſh Temptation.</p>
               <p>Beware dear Youth, of truſting to your own under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, or going out in your own ſtrength to combat Hell. You are not all <hi>Davids</hi> of ſufficient force to Duel it with the <hi>Goliah</hi> of Hell.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Do not commit any ſin preſuming on ſecrecy or Impunity, not on ſecrecy. For there is nothing hid but ſhall be revealed. Conſcience that Bird of the Air ſhall publiſh upon the Houſe top before Men and Angels, what you have done in your Privy Chambers. Angels ſee you, good and bad, and they ſhall Witneſs againſt you. God ſeeth you at all times. Who can hide himſelf from God that is every where, and knoweth all things? <hi>Darkneſs and light are both
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:96502:52"/>alike to him.</hi> Pſalm 139.1. to 13. and <hi>Job</hi> 34.21.22.</p>
               <p>Murderers have of all other ſinners preſumed moſt upon Secrecy, and yet how miraculouſly have they been detected? Dreams, Apparitions, and meer Circumſtances have detected and Convicted them.</p>
               <p>And ſuppoſe you might eſcape Scot-free as to man, is it poſſible you can eſcape the Juſtice of God? The Barbarous <hi>Malteſes</hi> ſpake ſound Doctrine, though they were out in their Application, when they ſaid of <hi>Paul,</hi> no doubt this man is a Murderer, whom though he hath eſcaped the Sea, yet vengeance ſuffereth not to live. God may forgive the Eternal, but will not remit the temporal puniſhment.</p>
               <p>If you eſcape a publick Execution, you ſhall never a private one. Kings may pardon what God will not. Some that have eſcaped the Gallows, could never eſcape the Scourges of their own Conſcience, which is Gods Vice-Gerent: Yea, though truly Penitent, yet have died either with grief of mind, or by the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate ſtroke of Heaven. <hi>Plymouth</hi> can afford an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the former many years ago; and <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhall of the Latter.</p>
               <p>A Gentleman whoſe name was <hi>Waſtraw</hi> a moſt bloody man, and other ways notorious for prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but moſt in this; that it was his great work, and pleaſure to put difference betwixt men, and as it was at that time very eaſie to engage them in blood, whileſt he had thus ſtirred up a neighbor Gentleman to kill another in that place, finding him after ſore troubled in mind, there anent, he told him more of that practiſe would be the beſt Cure, for he himſelf had killed Six, and at the firſt time was much diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted, but the longer he did continue, it became the more eaſie.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:96502:53"/>
               <p>But one day whileſt he was on ſuch an account, riding to a place where Two had tryſted to deſide a private Quarrel by Fighting, his Horſe ſtumbles on the ſide of a ſteep Rock, and he falls a great way down, his Sword falling out before him, yet without any hurt; and hereby ſuch a ſtrange piece of Providence tryſt and break in upon his Conſcience, ſo that he quits his Journey, turns home with great trouble and remorſe; a moſt kindly change following thereon, and for ſome years after witneſſed much tenderneſs and repentance by his afterwalk; ſpent much time alone, mourning before his death; and that day he died, having no viſible appearance thereof to thoſe who looked on, he was heard in his Chamber much Wreſtling in Prayer, and after long continuance thoſe of the Houſe were forced to break open the Door, getting no anſwer after their long knocking, and found him dead in the Room, but upon his knees in a Prayer poſture, and the whole blood of his body, which from every paſſage thereof had iſſued out, ſwimming about the Floor: It being viſible how all theſe paſſages were opened for that effect, a moſt aſtoniſhing inſtance declaring this to the world, though he pardon the iniquity of his people. Yet ſome ſins he will not let paſs without a viſible mark of his anger, but will take vengeance on their inventions. <hi>I have given you the Story in its own</hi> Scottiſh <hi>Dialect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Carry this ever upon your hearts, keep it in your minds that you have a Father and Maſter in Heaven, and that dayly tributes of obedience and Thanksgiving muſt be yielded by you unto him.</p>
               <p>That you are Gods Children, and Gods Servants, and you muſt Love, Honor, Reverence, and Obey the Lord, whoſe you are, and that you ought to ſerve him principally, in the firſt place, and continually to the very laſt.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:96502:53"/>
               <p>Remember you have pretious, never dying Souls, and theſe muſt be ſaved. Do not for fear of any mans diſpleaſure diſpleaſe God, and Damn your Souls. If you once come to neglect God, to turn your backs upon your known duties, God will abandon you: And if God leave you, woe, woe unto you!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My dear Youth,</hi> acquaint your ſelves with the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of ſecret Prayer. Be at leaſt once a day in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate upon your knees before God. Bear the Yoke of Chriſts Commandments, it is a Golden Yoke, his Yoke is eaſie, his Burden light. You have ſeen very lately a vaſt difference between the Service of God and of ſin. When Souls drudge for ſin, like a curſed Tyrant, it makes them dig their untimely Graves.</p>
               <p>Sin is neither profitable, nor honorable, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable. It puts you upon the baſeſt work, and pays the worſt wages. What fruit have ſinners had of ſin but ſhame? That Harveſt which they reap from the Seed of ſin, is nothing elſe but an heap of grief and deſperate ſorrows.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Receive warning and inſtruction from theſe dreadful providences. Do not boaſt nor glory over theſe wretches. You ſtand by Grace, be not high minded but fear, it is God withholds you from their ſins, and preſerves you from their Judgments.</p>
               <p>Our bleſſed and Famous Martyr Maſter <hi>Bradford</hi> never ſaw any Malefactor leading to Execution, but he would ſmite upon his breaſt and ſay, Here! Within me is the root of that matter, for which this man ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers? You can all ſay the ſame.</p>
               <p>Remember <hi>Lots</hi> Wiſe. If God erect <hi>A Pillar</hi> of <hi>Salt</hi> in <hi>Plymouth,</hi> if God Fire <hi>a Beacon</hi> upon <hi>Catdown,</hi> as God hath done in the Execution of theſe unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:96502:54"/>Creatures, here is the uſe you muſt make of them, to hear, and fear, and do no more any ſuch wickedneſs.</p>
               <p>They are become <hi>a Sign unto you.</hi> God hath made them your <hi>Examples,</hi> to the intent that you ſhould not luſt after evil things as they luſted.</p>
               <p>They are <hi>a Warning-piece</hi> ſhot off in your Ears, <hi>a Light-houſe</hi> preſented to your Eyes, that you might be kept from the paths of the Deſtroyer. Theſe things are happened, and fallen out now in your days, for Examples that you might take admonition upon whom the ends, the laſt, and worſt days of the World are come.</p>
               <p>The juſt Lord hath been in the midſt of us; he cannot do iniquity; every morning doth he bring his judgments to light, he faileth not. Oh! be not as the unjuſt that know no ſhame. When Gods judgments are come home, ſo near unto us, to our very Doors and Houſes, The Youth of <hi>Plymouth</hi> muſt learn righteouſneſs. If you will not be warned by others, God will make you a warning unto others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dear youth,</hi> remember, that all <hi>Poyſoners,</hi> all <hi>Dogs</hi> that Bark at Religion and Godly Perſons, all <hi>Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers,</hi> and <hi>Murderers,</hi> all <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>unnatural Children,</hi> all <hi>diſobedient,</hi> and <hi>undutiful Servants</hi> ſhall be driven out of Heaven, <hi>by this Token, by this Sign,</hi> that Two of <hi>Plymouth</hi> were lately by a very ſhameful and curſed death driven out of the <hi>Earth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:96502:54"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Art thou a Superior? A Maſter, or Parent, Friendly Reader? Then ſuffer the word of Exhortation.</head>
               <p n="1">1. STudy Chriſtian Oeconomicks, the Arts of well-ordering thy Family according to the Laws of Chriſt, and put them into practice. It was an excellent Order of our Church, full of religious Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that thoſe who Married, ſhould on their wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding day receive the Sacrament: Teaching us this Leſſon, that none ſhould enter upon Family charges, before they did well underſtand the nature of Family duties. Ah! how much is this neglected? Perſons get into a married life, and yet them Families, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and Children before they have any skill to govern themſelves, and neither skill nor will to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern s;uch as are under them.</p>
               <p>This is the true Source of all our miſchiefs, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary and Root of our abounding Prophaneneſs; and till there be a Reformation here in our reſpective Families, in Maſters, and Parents, I ſhall deſpair of ever meeting with it among Children, or Servants. If Children prove unnatural, and Servants ungover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, Why did you not teach them better? If you are ignorant of your duties, do not complain that they neglect theirs. If Poyſon and Murder come into a Family, it was becauſe the fear of God was not there.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>My dear Plimouthians,</hi> Give good Examples to thoſe that are under you. They are led more by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples than Precepts. They do not write after the beſt Copies, but thoſe that are neareſt hand. Oh! walk before God, before your Children, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in a perfect way. Read and Meditate upon the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:96502:55"/>101. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> There is a divine Platform of your whole duty. What Children learn from their Parents, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants from their Maſters, that do they inſtil and teach alſo unto their Children and Servants.</p>
               <p>The happineſs or wretchedneſs, the weal and woe of the next age depends upon the Education, and Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of this. Make not poſterity miſerable, nor your own Fleſh and Blood, your deareſt parts, your chiefeſt Goods to curſe you when you are dead and gone, for your cockering and indulgence to them.</p>
               <p>Live all the Sermons you hear, and be an Epiſtle of commendation of your Miniſters to your Children, Servants, Families, and the whole World. Let none under your roofs have occaſion to behold your miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages. They are natural Apes, imitating what is had, not what is good. Keep your ſelves from all ſin, and keep the ſight of ſin from all that belong un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. If Children and Servants inſtead of Praying, hear Swearing and Curſing, inſtead of the Bible and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſms, bloody Oaths and Blaſpheming, inſtead of ſeeing Holineſs, and the ſhining beauties of Godlineſs, ſhall be the Spectators of their Parents wickedneſs and uncleanneſs, Atheiſm and Irreligion; Mark it, Sirs, Mark what I tell you, without Miracles of mercy, you, and your Children, and your Servants, and your Houſes ſhall be undone Eternally. <hi>The curſe of the Lord is it to the Houſe of the Wicked, but he bleſſeth the Habitation of the Juſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. My dear Townſmen, Perform Family duties, let them not grow out of uſe and faſhion. Whatever others do, yet do you and your Families ſerve the Lord. Give God a Morning and Evening Sacrifice of Prayer and Thankſgiving. <hi>He hath throatned to pour out his wrath upon the Families that call not upon his Name.</hi> Jer. 10. <hi>ult.</hi> Prayerleſs Families, are Paganiſh Families, and Heathen Families are loathed by God.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:96502:55"/>
               <p>Read the Scriptures daily in your Houſes, Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chize and Inſtruct in the doctrinals of Religion the Youth within your Gates. Repeat, and frequently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with them about the Word of God read, and preached. Sanctifie the Lords day. Sing <hi>Pſalms,</hi> and the high-ſounding Praiſes of God in your dwellings. Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Proficiency of your Children, and Servants in the grace and knowledg of our Lord and Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. Give due and ſeaſonable reprehenſion and correction, and ſpare not the Rod, unleſs you will ſpoil the Child. Comfort and incourage them in well-doing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Preſs them to private duties, and give them time for Cloſet-prayer; and do you endeavor to bring them to the publick Worſhip and Ordinances, eſpecially to the Sacraments. Remember that they who ſerve God moſt, will ſerve you beſt; that a graceleſs Servant is a Devil in your Family, which will ruin himſelf, and you, and yours alſo.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Conſider with your ſelves that you have the charge of Souls, there is a great truſt committed from Heaven unto Governours of Families. The Lord Treaſurer of the Kingdom hath no ſuch Jewels, nor Treaſure in the Exchequer, as you have in your Houſes. God hath made you the Guardians and Truſtees of pretious Souls, and as ſure as you live, ſhall you be reſponſible for them unto God. Do your utmoſt that none miſcarry under your hands. Prefer the concerns of their Souls to thoſe of your Bodies, and be at as much care and pains that they may live in Heaven, as you and yours to live on Earth. You are their beſt and ſureſt Friends, if faſt and faithful Friends unto their Souls. To ruin a Soul is the Trick and Work of Devils, it is an irreparable loſs, an everlaſting evil. Loſt Goods may be recovered, but if a Soul be once damned, either by your ſins of omiſſion or commiſſion, it can never be recovered more. The Lord deliver you from the Guilt of Soul-Murder.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:96502:56"/>
               <p n="5">5. When you diſpoſe your Children abroad in the World, get them into Religious Families, that they may drive a thriving trade Heaven-ward, and obtain the Inheritance of Gods Saints, his pretious promiſes. It is not Riches, nor Honors, nor great dealings in the VVorld; but Godlineſs that hath the promiſes of this life, and of that which is to come.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Are your Relations and Inferiors, your Children and Servants wicked, and irreligi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us? do you become better. Let not their ſins be juſty charged on your Souls. Shortly, VVhen death is in your Pot, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member nothing but the Grace of God can preſerve you. Therefore value, and prize it. Did Servants do it? Conſider, that it is juſt with God, they ſhould be Inſtruments of your deſtruction, when your neglect of their Religious Education, is a real cauſe of their Trangreſſion. They muſt go to Heaven as well as you, and therefore ſhould injoy liberties, and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities for the ſolemn, and publick Worſhip of God as well as your ſelves.</p>
               <p>The Gallows and Stake, the Fire and Halter preach unto Young and Old, High and Low, Parents and Children, Maſters and Servant this Doctrin, <hi>That un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you do Repent, you ſhall alſo periſh.</hi> Gods judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon others, are warnings unto us. It is an Oracle from Heaven, That ſuch who ſin as others, ſhall periſh as others: That if you do not repent, the wrath of God which lighted upon others, ſhall either here, or hereafter infallibly, and to all eternity light down upon you alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:96502:56"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
